<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="fr">
                   <page>
                      <title>Organisation</title>
                        <ns>0</ns>
                        <id>0</id>
                        <revision>
                          <id>0</id>
                          <timestamp>2020-07-08T20:09:21Z</timestamp>
                          <contributor>
                            <username>Romain</username>
                            <id>1</id>
                          </contributor>
                          <comment>organization
PMID: 16353909.AA</comment>
                          <model>wikitext</model>
                          <format>text/x-wiki</format><text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12">organization
PMID: 16353909.AAPS J. 2005 Sep 22;7(2):E274-80. Review. The joint food and agriculture organization of the United Nations/World Health Organization Expert Committee on Food Additives and its role in the evaluation of the safety of veterinary drug residues in foods.
An entity that can bear roles, has members, and has a set of organization rules. Members of organizations are either organizations themselves or individual people. Members can bear specific organization member roles that are determined in the organization rules. The organization rules also determine how decisions are made on behalf of the organization by the organization members.
Une entité qui peut occuper des rôles, possède des membres et possède un ensemble de règles d&apos;organisation. Les membres des organisations sont soit des organisations elles-mêmes, soit des personnes individuelles. Les membres peuvent occuper des rôles spécifiques des membres de l&apos;organisation qui sont déterminés dans les règles de l&apos;organisation. Les règles de l&apos;organisation déterminent également les décisions prises par les membres de l&apos;organisation pour le compte de l&apos;organisation.
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
PERSON: Susanna Sansone
GROUP: OBI
 is a subclass from http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/BFO_0000040
</text>
                          <sha1>753hugogitqwnlby9d3k5rdzsa58oj1</sha1>
                        </revision>
                      </page>
                    </mediawiki>