<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="fr">
                   <page>
                      <title>Plan dye swap</title>
                        <ns>0</ns>
                        <id>0</id>
                        <revision>
                          <id>0</id>
                          <timestamp>2020-07-08T19:59:45Z</timestamp>
                          <contributor>
                            <username>Romain</username>
                            <id>1</id>
                          </contributor>
                          <comment>dye swap design
PMID: 17411393</comment>
                          <model>wikitext</model>
                          <format>text/x-wiki</format><text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12">dye swap design
PMID: 17411393-Dye-specific bias effects, commonly observed in the two-color microarray platform, are normally corrected using the dye swap design. This design, however, is relatively expensive and labor-intensive. We propose a self-self hybridization design as an alternative to the dye swap design. In this design, the treated and control samples are labeled with Cy5 and Cy3 (or Cy3 and Cy5), respectively, without dye swap, along with a set of self-self hybridizations on the control sample. We compare this design with the dye swap design through investigation of mouse primary hepatocytes treated with three peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-alpha (PPARalpha) agonists at three dose levels. Using Agilent&apos;s Whole Mouse Genome microarray, differentially expressed genes (DEG) were determined for both the self-self hybridization and dye swap designs. The DEG concordance between the two designs was over 80% across each dose treatment and chemical. Furthermore, 90% of DEG-associated biological pathways were in common between the designs, indicating that biological interpretations would be consistent. The reduced labor and expense for the self-self hybridization design make it an efficient substitute for the dye swap design. For example, in larger toxicogenomic studies, only about half the chips are required for the self-self hybridization design compared to that needed in the dye swap design.
An experiment design type where the label orientations are reversed. exact synonym: flip dye, dye flip
Un type de conception d&apos;expérience où les orientations de l&apos;étiquette sont inversées. Synonyme exact: flip dye, dye flip
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra on behalf of MO
MO_858
</text>
                          <sha1>753hugogitqwnlby9d3k5rdzsa58oj1</sha1>
                        </revision>
                      </page>
                    </mediawiki>