<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="fr">
                   <page>
                      <title>Région spatiale</title>
                        <ns>0</ns>
                        <id>0</id>
                        <revision>
                          <id>0</id>
                          <timestamp>2020-07-08T19:59:55Z</timestamp>
                          <contributor>
                            <username>Romain</username>
                            <id>1</id>
                          </contributor>
                          <comment>example to be eventually remov</comment>
                          <model>wikitext</model>
                          <format>text/x-wiki</format><text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12">example to be eventually removed
metadata complete
Class has all its metadata, but is either not guaranteed to be in its final location in the asserted IS_A hierarchy or refers to another class that is not complete.
organizational term
term created to ease viewing/sort terms for development purpose, and will not be included in a release
PERSON:Alan Ruttenberg
ready for release
Class has undergone final review, is ready for use, and will be included in the next release. Any class lacking &quot;ready_for_release&quot; should be considered likely to change place in hierarchy, have its definition refined, or be obsoleted in the next release.Those classes deemed &quot;ready_for_release&quot; will also derived from a chain of ancestor classes that are also &quot;ready_for_release.&quot;
metadata incomplete
Class is being worked on; however, the metadata (including definition) are not complete or sufficiently clear to the branch editors.
uncurated
Nothing done yet beyond assigning a unique class ID and proposing a preferred term.
pending final vetting
All definitions, placement in the asserted IS_A hierarchy and required minimal metadata are complete. The class is awaiting a final review by someone other than the term editor.
to be replaced with external ontology term
Terms with this status should eventually replaced with a term from another ontology.
Alan Ruttenberg
group:OBI
requires discussion
A term that is metadata complete, has been reviewed, and problems have been identified that require discussion before release. Such a term requires editor note(s) to identify the outstanding issues.
Alan Ruttenberg
group:OBI
a false positive rate whose value is 5 per cent
Following discussion with OBCS, deprecated of class STATO_0000043 and creation of instance
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
a false positive rate whose value is 1 per cent
Following discussion with OBCS, deprecated of class STATO_0000281 and creation of instance
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
entity
the sum total of all space in the universe
spatial region
Space and spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] entities are entities in their own rights which exist independently of any entities which can be located at them. This view of space is sometimes called &quot;absolutist&quot; or &quot;the container view&quot;. In BFO, the class site [snap:Site] allows for a so-called relational view of space, that is to say, a view according to which spatiality is a matter of relative location between entities and not a matter of being tied to space. The bridge between these two views is secured through the fact that while instances of site [snap:Site] are not spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] entities, they are nevertheless spatial entities.
All instances of continuant [snap:Continuant] are spatial entities, that is, they enter in the relation of (spatial) location with spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] entities. As a particular case, the exact spatial location of a spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] is this region itself.
parts of the sum total of all space in the universe
Adaptée de http://www.hypergeo.eu/spip.php?article14
An instance of spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] is a part of space. All parts of space are spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] entities and only spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion] entities are parts of space. Space is the entire extent of the spatial universe, a designated individual, which is thus itself a spatial region [snap:SpatialRegion].
Jean-Marc Meunier
C&apos;est une portion de l’espacequ’un critère particulier permet d’individualiser, en la détachant de son environnement.
A continuantthat is neither bearer of qualityentities nor inheres in any other entities.
the surface of a rectilinear planar figure-shaped part of space
Jean-Marc Meunier
Région spatiale à deux dimensions
the surface of a cube-shaped part of space
A spatial regionwith two dimensions.
two dimensional region
the surface of a sphere-shaped part of space
Jean-Marc Meunier
Prédisposition
the disposition of blood to coagulate
the disposition of vegetables to decay when not refrigerated
the disposition of metal to conduct electricity
Une entité réalisable qui provoque essentiellement un processus ou une transformation spécifique de l&apos;objet dans lequel elle est inhérente, dans des circonstances particulières et en conjonction avec les lois de la nature. Une formule générale pour les dispositions est: X (l&apos;objet a la disposition D (transformer, initier un processus) R dans les conditions C.
the disposition of a patient with a weakened immune system to contract disease
A realizable entitythat essentially causes a specific process or transformation in the objectin which it inheres, under specific circumstances and in conjunction with the laws of nature. A general formula for dispositions is: X (objecthas the disposition D to (transform, initiate a process) R under conditions C.
the disposition of a vase to brake if dropped
disposition
Jean-Marc Meunier
A specifically dependent continuantthat inheres in continuantentities and are not exhibited in full at every time in which it inheres in an entity or group of entities. The exhibition or actualization of a realizable entity is a particular manifestation, functioning or process that occurs under certain circumstances.
If a realizable entity [snap:RealizableEntity] inheres in a continuant [snap:Continuant], this does not imply that it is actually realized.
the disposition of blood to coagulate
Un continuant spécifiquement dépendant qui est inhérent aux continuants et qui ne sont pas exposés en entier à chaque fois qu&apos;il est inhérent à une entité ou à un groupe d&apos;entités. L&apos;exposition ou l&apos;actualisation d&apos;une entité réalisable est une manifestation, un fonctionnement ou un processus particulier qui se produit dans certaines circonstances.
J&apos;ai un doute sur ma traduction
the function of the reproductive organs
realizable entity
the disposition of metal to conduct electricity
the role of being a doctor
a point
A spatial regionwith no dimensions.
zero dimensional region
Jean-Marc Meunier
Région spatial sans dimension
Jean-Marc Meunier
Région spatial à une dimension.
the part of space that is a line stretching from one end of absolute space to the other
A spatial regionwith one dimension.
an edge of a cube-shaped part of space
one dimensional region
a cube-shaped part of space
Jean-marc Meunier
Région spatial à trois dimensions.
three dimensional region
a sphere-shaped part of space
A spatial regionwith three dimensions.
the function of a birth canal to enable transport
Jean-Marc Meunier
the digestive function of the stomach to nutriate the body
the function of reproduction in the transmission of genetic material
the function of the heart in the body: to pump blood, to receive de-oxygenated and oxygenated blood, etc.
function
Entité réalisable donr la manifestation est essentiellement orientée vers une activité finalisée d&apos;un continuant en vertue de quoi le continuant est une sorte spécifiqu d&apos;entité dans le où les types de conte

the function of a computer program to compute mathematical equations
A realizable entitythe manifestation of which is an essentially end-directed activity of a continuantentity in virtue of that continuantentity being a specific kind of entity in the kind or kinds of contexts that it is made for.
Fonction
the function of a hammer to drive in nails
the function of a judge in a court of law
the function of an automobile to provide transportation
Un continuant indépendantspatialement situé dont l&apos;identité est indépendante de celle d&apos;autres entités et peut être maintenue dans le temps.
Jean-Marc Meunier
material entity
Material entity [snap:MaterialEntity] subsumes object [snap:Object], fiat object part [snap:FiatObjectPart], and object aggregate [snap:ObjectAggregate], which assume a three level theory of granularity, which is inadequate for some domains, such as biology.
Examples: collection of random bacteria, a chair, dorsal surface of the body
An independent continuantthat is spatially extended whose identity is independent of that of other entities and can be maintained through time.
gross anatomical part
Anatomical structure that is part of a multicellular organism and is at the gross anatomical level, e.g. above the level of a cell.Included are portions of organism substances such as blood, multi-cell-part structures such as axon tracts, acellular anatomical structures such as hair, and organism subdivisions such as head. Excluded is the whole organism and more granular parts of the organism, such as atoms, molecules, macromolecular complexes and cells.
nucleic acid
A macromolecule made up of nucleotide units and hydrolysable into certain pyrimidine or purine bases (usually adenine, cytosine, guanine, thymine, uracil), D-ribose or 2-deoxy-D-ribose and phosphoric acid.
cell
PMID:18089833.Cancer Res. 2007 Dec 15;67(24):12018-25. &quot;...Epithelial cells were harvested from histologically confirmed adenocarcinomas ..&quot;
A material entity of anatomical origin (part of or deriving from an organism) that has as its parts a maximally connected cell compartment surrounded by a plasma membrane.
cultured cell
A cell in vitro that is or has been maintained or propagated as part of a cell culture.
experimentally modified cell in vitro
A cell in vitro that has undergone physical changes as a consequence of a deliberate and specific experimental procedure.
The process in which a gene&apos;s sequence is converted into a mature gene product or products (proteins or RNA). This includes the production of an RNA transcript as well as any processing to produce a mature RNA product or an mRNA (for protein-coding genes) and the translation of that mRNA into protein. Some protein processing events may be included when they are required to form an active form of a product from an inactive precursor form.
gene expression
protein complex
A ribosome is a protein complex
Any macromolecular complex composed of two or more polypeptide subunits, which may or may not be identical. Protein complexes may have other associated non-protein prosthetic groups, such as nucleotides, metal ions or other small molecules.
PERSON: Barry Smith
Une directive qui décrit le résultat prévu d&apos;un processus
OBI_0000217
objective specification
OBI Plan and Planned Process/Roles Branch
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
a directive information entity that describes an intended process endpoint. 
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
PERSON: Jennifer Fostel
Answers the question, why did you do this experiment?
Une directive qui décrit l&apos;action que le porteur fera.
Alan Ruttenberg
Pour the contents of flask 1 into flask 2
OBI Plan and Planned Process branch
a directive information entity that describes an action the bearer will take
action specification
Jean-Marc Meunier
Donnée statistique
data item
Jean-Marc Meunier
2/2/2009 Alan and Bjoern discussing FACS run output data. This is a data item because it is about the cell population. Each element records an event and is typically further composed a set of measurment data items that record the fluorescent intensity stimulated by one of the lasers.
An information content entity that is intended to be a truthful statement about something (modulo, e.g., measurement precision or other systematic errors) and is constructed/acquired by a method that reliably tends to produce (approximately) truthful statements.
2009-03-16: removed datum as alternative term as datum specifically refers to singular form, and is thus not an exact synonym.
Traduction à discuter.
Data items include counts of things, analyte concentrations, and statistical summaries.
Une entité support d&apos;information d&apos;information pouvantêtredéclarée vraie à propos de quelque chose (modulo, par exemple, la précision de mesure ou d&apos;autres erreurs systématiques) et est construit / acquis par une méthode objective.
data
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
PERSON: Chris Stoeckert
PERSON: Jonathan Rees
2009-03-16: data item deliberatly ambiguous: we merged data set and datum to be one entity, not knowing how to define singular versus plural. So data item is more general than datum.
Examples of information content entites include journal articles, data, graphical layouts, and graphs.
an information content entity is an entity that is generically dependent on some material entity and stands in relation of aboutness to some entity
OBI_0000142
information content entity
PERSON: Chris Stoeckert
une entité support d&apos;information est une entité qui dépend génériquement d&apos;une entité matérielle et est en relation avec une entité.
Jean-Marc Meunier
scalar measurement datum
Would write this as: has_part some &apos;measurement unit label&apos; and has_part some numeral and has_part exactly 2, except for the fact that this won&apos;t let us take advantage of OWL reasoning over the numbers. Instead use has measurment value property to represent the same. Use has measurement unit label (subproperty of has_part) so we can easily say that there is only one of them.
10 feet. 3 ml.
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
Une donnée de mesure scalaire est une donnée de mesure composée de deux parties, des chiffres et une étiquette d&apos;unité.
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
a scalar measurement datum is a measurement datum that is composed of two parts, numerals and a unit label.
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
Werner pushed back on calling it realizable information entity as it isn&apos;t realizable. However this name isn&apos;t right either. An example would be a recipe. The realizable entity would be a plan, but the information entity isn&apos;t about the plan, it, once concretized, *is* the plan. -Alan
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
Philly2013 - AR: What differentiates a directive information entity from an information concretization is that it can have concretizations that are either qualities or realizable entities. The concretizations that are realizable entities are created when an individual chooses to take up the direction, i.e. has the intention to (try to) realize it.
8/6/2009 Alan Ruttenberg: Changed label from &quot;information entity about a realizable&quot; after discussions at ICBO
Une entité support d&apos;information dont les concrétisations indiquent à leur porteur comment les réaliser dans un processus.
An information content entity whose concretizations indicate to their bearer how to realize them in a process.
Jean-Marc Meunier
directive information entity
MSI
a rule is an executable which guides, defines, restricts actions
rule
PRS
OBI_0500021
PRS
Une règle est un exécutable qui guide, définit ou restreint les actions
example to be added
GROUP: OBI
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
2009-03-16: this was report of results with definition: A report is a narrative object that is a formal statement of the results of an investigation, or of any matter on which definite information is required, made by some person or body instructed or required to do so.
journal article, patent application, grant progress report, case report (not patient record)
PERSON:Chris Stoeckert
report
disagreement about where reports go. alan: only some gene lists are reports. Is a report all the content of some document? The example of usage suggests that a report may be part ofsome article. Term needs clarification
An information content entity assembled by an author for the purpose of providing information for an audience, and that is meant to provide an accurate account of something that happened.
Une entité support d&apos;informations réunies par un auteur dans le but de fournir des informations à un public, et qui est destiné à fournir un compte rendu exact de quelque chose qui s&apos;est passé.
2009-08-10 Alan Ruttenberg: Larry Hunter suggests that this be obsoleted and replaced by &apos;document&apos;. Alan restored as there are OBI dependencies and this merits further discussion
OBI_0000099
2009-03-16: work has been done on this term during during the OBI workshop winter 2009 and the current definition was considered acceptable for use in OBI. If there is a need to modify this definition please notify OBI.
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
Intensity values in a CEL file or from multiple CEL files comprise a data set (as opposed to the CEL files themselves).
data set
Un élément de données qui est un ensemble d&apos;autres éléments de données du même type et qui ont quelque chose en commun. Les moyennes et les distributions peuvent être déterminées pour les ensembles de données.
person:Chris Stoeckert
group:OBI
person:Allyson Lister
Jean-Marc Meunier
A data item that is an aggregate of other data items of the same type that have something in common. Averages and distributions can be determined for data sets.
2009/10/23 Alan Ruttenberg. The intention is that this term represent collections of like data. So this isn&apos;t for, e.g. the whole contents of a cel file, which includes parameters, metadata etc. This is more like java arrays of a certain rather specific type
OBI_0000042
image
person:Chris Stoeckert
person:Alan Ruttenberg
group:OBI
person:Allyson
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une image est une projection affine sur une surface bidimensionnelle, des mesures d&apos;une certaine qualité d&apos;une entité ou d&apos;entités répétées à intervalles réguliers sur une plage spatiale, où les mesures sont représentées par la couleur et la luminosité sur la surface projetée.
OBI_0000030
An image is an affine projection to a two dimensional surface, of measurements of some quality of an entity or entities repeated at regular intervals across a spatial range, where the measurements are represented as color and luminosity on the projected on surface.
Un plan est un ensemble d&apos;instructions qui précisent comment un objectif doit être atteint.
Alan Ruttenberg
plan specification
2009-03-16: provenance: a term a plan was proposed for OBI (OBI_0000344) , edited by the PlanAndPlannedProcess branch. Original definition was &quot; a plan is a specification of a process that is realized by an actor to achieve the objective specified as part of the plan&quot;. It has been subsequently moved to IAO where the objective for which the original term was defined was satisfied with the definitionof this, different, term.
a directive information entity that, when concretized, is realized in a process in which the bearer tries to achieve the objectives, in part by taking the actions specified.
Jean-Marc Meunier
OBI_0000344
OBI Plan and Planned Process branch
Alternative previous definition: a plan is a set of instructions that specify how an objective should be achieved
To lose weight, go running daily for at least 30 minutes. To isolate plasmafrom blood, centrifuge tubes at 1100-1300 rpm for 15 minutes.
Jean-Marc Meunier
group:OBI
OBI_0000305
Examples of measurement data are the recoding of the weight of a mouse as {40,mass,&quot;grams&quot;}, the recording of an observation of the behavior of the mouse {,process,&quot;agitated&quot;}, the recording of the expression level of a gene as measured through the process of microarray experiment {3.4,luminosity,}.
A data item that is a recording of the output of an assay.
person:Chris Stoeckert
measurement data item
measurement datum
C&apos;est une donnée résultant d&apos;une mesure au cours d&apos;un essai.
2/2/2009 is_specified_output of some assay?
version number
A version number is an information content entity which is a sequence of characters borne by part of each of a class of manufactured products or its packaging and indicates its order within a set of other products having the same name.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Un numéro de version est un support d&apos;information constituée d&apos;une chaine de caractères indiquant l&apos;ordre de production des entités de même nom.
GROUP: IAO
Note: we feel that at the moment we are happy with a general version number, and that we will subclass as needed in the future. For example, see 7. genome sequence version
Person:Alan Ruttenberg
conclusion textual entity
that fucoidan has a small statistically significant effect on AT3 level but no useful clinical effect as in-vivo anticoagulant, a paraphrase of part of the last paragraph of the discussion section of the paper &apos;Pilot clinical study to evaluate the anticoagulant activity of fucoidan&apos;, by Lowenthal et. al.PMID:19696660
2009/09/28 Alan Ruttenberg. Fucoidan-use-case
2009/10/23 Alan Ruttenberg: We need to work on the definition still
A textual entity that expresses the results of reasoning about a problem, for instance as typically found towards the end of scientific papers.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une entité textuelle qui exprime le résultat d&apos;un raisonnement à propos d&apos;un problème, par exemple tel qu&apos;on en trouve typiquement à la fin des articles scientifiques
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON:Melanie Courtot
PERSON:Chris Stoeckert
scatter plot
Un diagramme de dispersion est un graphique qui utilise des coordonnées cartésiennes pour afficher des valeurs pour deux variables pour un ensemble de données. Les données sont affichées comme une collection de points, chacun ayant la valeur d&apos;une variable déterminant la position sur l&apos;axe horizontal et la valeur de l&apos;autre variable déterminant la position sur l&apos;axe vertical.
scattergraph
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scatterplot
A scatterplot is a graph which uses Cartesian coordinates to display values for two variables for a set of data. The data is displayed as a collection of points, each having the value of one variable determining the position on the horizontal axis and the value of the other variable determining the position on the vertical axis.
PERSON:James Malone
Comparison of gene expression values in two samples can be displayed in a scatter plot
Une entité textuelle qui contient un arrangement bidimensionnel de textes répétés à intervalles réguliers dans un arrangement spatial, de sorte que les relations spatiales entre les textes qui le composent expriment des propositions.
PERSON: Lawrence Hunter
Jean-Marc Meunier
A textual entity that contains a two-dimensional arrangement of texts repeated at regular intervals across a spatial range, such that the spatial relationships among the constituent texts expresses propositions
table
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alan Ruttenberg
Une donnée de coordonnées spatiales cartésiennes est une représentation d&apos;un point dans une région spatiale, dans lequel des changements égaux dans la grandeur d&apos;une valeur de coordonnées désignent des qualités de longueur de même ampleur.
cartesian spatial coordinate datum
2009-08-18 Alan Ruttenberg - question to BFO list about whether the BFO sense of the lower dimensional regions is that they are always part of actual space (the three dimensional sort) http://groups.google.com/group/bfo-discuss/browse_thread/thread/9d04e717e39fb617
A cartesian spatial coordinate datum is a representation of a point in a spatial region, in which equal changes in the magnitude of a coordinate value denote length qualities with the same magnitude
wikipedia http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Documenting
Bjoern Peters
documenting
Recording the current temperature in a laboratory notebook. Writing a journal article. Updating a patient record in a database. Copying the readout from an instrument into a spreadsheet.
Un processus planifié dans lequel les informations d&apos;entrée sont utilisées pour créer ou ajouter à un rapport.
6/11/9: Edited at OBI workshop. We need to be able identify a child form of information artifact which corresponds to something enduring (not brain like). This used to be restricted to physical document or digital entity as the output, but that excludes e.g. an audio cassette tape
a planned process in which input information is used to create or add to a report
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
A symbol that is sufficient to look up information about the corresponding entity from its CRID (centrally registered identifier) registry.
IAO call, 20101124: 12345 is not a CRID symbol. To be a CRID symbol you need to have some information about the registry within which the CRID is recorded.
CRID
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
Original proposal from Bjoern, discussions at IAO calls
Jean-Marc Meunier
PubMed identifier “PMID:12345”
PERSON: Bill Hogan
centrally registered identifier
The following URL: &quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19918065&quot;
Centrally Registered IDentifier (CRID)
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
Entries in a Column of which the header is &quot;Pubmed ID&quot; 
Note, IAO call 20101124: URIs are not always CRID, as not centrally registered. We acknowledge that CRID is a subset of a larger identifier class, but this subset fulfills our current needs. OBI PURLs are CRID as they are registered with OCLC. UPCs (Universal Product Codes from AC Nielsen)are not CRID as they are not centrally registered.
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
Original proposal from Bjoern, discussions at IAO calls
PMID:12345
Jean-Marc Meunier
centrally registered identifier
An information content entity that consists of a CRID symbol and additional information about which CRID registry it belongs. 
Une entité support d&apos;information qui se compose d&apos;un symbole CRID et d&apos;informations supplémentaires sur le registre CRID auquel il appartient.
The following sentence contains a CRID: &quot;The article with Pubmed ID: 19918065&quot;. 
PERSON: Bill Hogan
time stamped measurement datum
C&apos;est un ensemble de données qui combine des mesures à un certain nombre de points temporels. L&apos;ensemble de données de la série temporelle est une liste ordonnée de paires de données de mesure du temps et les données de mesure correspondantes acquises à ce moment-là.
pmid:20604925 - time-lapse live cell microscopy
time sampled measurement data set
Jean-Marc Meunier
experimental time series
A data set that is an aggregate of data recording some measurement at a number of time points. The time series data set is an ordered list of pairs of time measurement data and the corresponding measurement data acquired at that time.
Alan Ruttenberg
From the DT branch: This term and definition were originally submitted by the community to our branch, but we thought they best fit DENRIE. However we see several issues with this. First of all the name &apos;probe&apos; might not be used in OBI. Instead we have a &apos;reporter&apos; role. Also, albeit the term &apos;probe intensity&apos; is often used in communities such as the microarray one, the name &apos;probe&apos; is ambiguous (some use it to refer to what&apos;s on the array, some use it to refer to what&apos;s hybed to the array). Furthermore, this concept could possibly be encompassed by combining different OBI terms, such as the roles of analyte, detector and reporter (you need something hybed to a probe on the array to get an intensity) and maybe a more general term for &apos;measuring intensities&apos;. We need to find the right balance between what is consistent with OBI and combinations of its terms and what is user-friendly. Finally, note that &apos;intensity&apos; is already in the OBI .owl file and is also in PATO. Why didn&apos;t OBI import it from PATO? This might be a problem.
A measurement datum that represents the output of a scanner measuring the intensity value for each fluorescent reporter.
group:OBI
person:Chris Stoeckert
fluorescent reporter intensity
Is a material entity that is created or changed during material processing.
Examples include gel matrices, filter paper, parafilm and buffer solutions, mass spectrometer, tissue samples
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
processed material
investigation
Bjoern Peters
a planned process that consists of parts: planning, study design execution, documentation and which produce conclusion(s).
Investigation
Jean-Marc Meunier
Could add specific objective specification
Un processus planifié qui comprend plusieurs parties : la planification, l&apos;exécution du plan d&apos;étude, la documentation et la production de conclusion.
OBI branch derived
Lung cancer investigation using expression profiling, a stem cell transplant investigation, biobanking is not an investigation, though it may be part of an investigation
Feb 10, 2009.changes after discussion at OBI Consortium Workshop Feb 2-6, 2009.accepted as core term.
OBI
GROUP:Role Branch
When a specimen of blood is assayed for glucose concentration, the blood has the evaluant role. When measuring the mass of a mouse, the evaluant is the mouse. When measuring the time of DNA replication, the evaluant is the DNA. When measuring the intensity of light on a surface, the evaluant is the light source.
evaluant role
examples of features that could be described in an evaluant: quality.... e.g. &quot;contains 10 pg/ml IL2&quot;, or &quot;no glucose detected&quot;)
Role call - 17nov-08: JF and MC think an evaluant role is always specified input of a process. Even in the case where we have an assay taking blood as evaluant and outputting blood, the blood is not the specified output at the end of the assay (the concentration of glucose in the blood is)
a role that inheres in a material entity that is realized in an assay in which data is generated about the bearer of the evaluant role
scientific observation
measuring
PlanAndPlannedProcess Branch
OBI branch derived
12/3/12: BP: the reference to the &apos;physical examination&apos; is included to point out that a prediction is not an assay, as that does not require physical examiniation. 
assay
A planned process with the objective to produce information about the material entity that is the evaluant, by physically examining it or its proxies.
Assay the wavelength of light emitted by excited Neon atoms. Count of geese flying over a house.
OBI
A growth medium or culture medium is a substance in which microorganisms or cells can grow.Wikipedia, growth medium, Feb 29, 2008
culture medium
a processed material that provides the needed nourishment for microorganisms or cells grown in vitro.
Person: Jennifer Fostel, Jie Zheng
A planned process which results in physical changes in a specified input material
material transformation
OBI branch derived
material processing
Un processus planifié qui résulte d&apos;un changement physique d&apos;un matériel spécifié en entrée.
A cell lysis, production of a cloning vector, creating a buffer.
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
PERSON: Frank Gibson
PERSON: Philippe Rocca Serra
PERSON: Jennifer Fostel
sequence feature identification objective
Jennifer Fostel
Sequence_feature_identification_objective is a biological_feature_identification_objective role describing a study designed to examine or characterize molecular features exhibited at the level of a macromolecular sequence, e.g. nucleic acid, protein, polysaccharide.
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
PMID:6110205. collection of cDNA derived from mouse splenocytes.
PERSON: Luisa Montecchi
cDNA library
GROUP: PSI
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P-value
PERSON:Chris Stoeckert
May be outside the scope of OBI long term, is needed so is retained
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Dans un test statistique, la valeur-p (en anglais p-value), parfois aussi appelée p-valeur, est la probabilité d&apos;obtenir la même valeur (ou une valeur encore plus extrême) du test si l&apos;hypothèse nulle était vraie. Contrairement à ce qui est parfois écrit, la valeur-p n&apos;est pas la probabilité que l&apos;hypothèse nulle soit vraie.
Addition of restriction &apos;output of null hypothesis testing&apos; by AGB and PRS while working on STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valeur_p
A quantitative confidence value that represents the probability of obtaining a result at least as extreme as that actually obtained, assuming that the actual value was the result of chance alone.
p-value
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Population
adapted from Oxford English Dictionnary
Jean-Marc Meunier
rem1: collection somehow always involve a selection process
Une population est un ensemble d&apos;individus ou d&apos;éléments partageant une ou plusieurs caractéristiques qui servent à les regrouper. On parle ainsi de population humaine, population statistique, de population biologique, population civile, etc.
population
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
a population is a collection of individuals from the same taxonomic class living, counted or sampled at a particular site or in a particular area
PMID12564891. Environ Sci Technol. 2003 Jan 15;37(2):223-8. Effects of historic PCB exposures on the reproductive success of the Hudson River striped bass population.
D&apos;un point de vue statistiques, une population ne revoie pas toujours à un collection d&apos;entités vivantes
An imaging assay is an assay to produce a picture of an entity. definition_source: OBI.
PlanAndPlannedProcess Branch
OBI branch derived
imaging assay
Protocole d&apos;expérimentation
PlanAndPlannedProcess Branch
OBI branch derived + wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protocol_%28natural_sciences%29)
PCR protocol, has objective specification, amplify DNA fragment of interest, and has action specification describes the amounts of experimental reagents used (e..g. buffers, dNTPS, enzyme), and the temperature and cycle time settings for running the PCR.
Protocole d&apos;étude
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%A9thode_exp%C3%A9rimentale

Le protocole d&apos;expérimentation regroupe la description des conditions et du déroulement d&apos;une expérience ou d&apos;un test. La description doit être suffisamment claire afin que l&apos;expérience puisse être reproduite à l&apos;identique et il doit faire l&apos;objet d&apos;une analyse critique pour notamment détecter d&apos;éventuels biais.
A plan specification which has sufficient level of detail and quantitative information to communicate it between investigation agents, so that different investigation agents will reliably be able to independently reproduce the process.
protocol
Class was renamed from &apos;administering substance&apos;, as this is commonly used only for additions into organisms.
branch derived
is a process with the objective to place a material entity bearing the &apos;material to be added role&apos; into a material bearing the &apos;target of material addition role&apos;.
Injecting a drug into a mouse. Adding IL-2 to a cell culture. Adding NaCl into water.
adding a material entity into a target
BP
analyte role
Glucose in blood (measured in an assay to determine the concentration of glucose).
A role borne by a molecular entity or an atom and realized in an analyte assay which achieves the objective to measure the magnitude/concentration/amount of the analyte in the entity bearing evaluant role
GROUP: Role Branch
qualities such as weight, color are not assayed but measured, so they do not fall into this category.
pH (technically the inverse log of [H+]) may be considered a quality; this remains to be tested.
interestingly, an analyte is still an analyte even if it is not detected.for this reason it does not bear a specified input role
OBI
Feb 10, 2009.changes after discussion at OBI Consortium Workshop Feb 2-6, 2009.accepted as core term.
9 March 09 from discussion with PA branch
OBI
material to be added role is a protocol participant role realized by a material which is added into a material bearing the target of material addition role in a material addition process
material to be added role
Role Branch
drug added to a buffer contained in a tube; substance injected into an animal;
A planned process in which data gathered in an investigation is evaluated in the context of existing knowledge with the objective to generate more general conclusions or to conclude that the data does not allow one to draw general conclusion
Concluding that a gene is upregulated in a tissue sample based on the band intensity in a western blot.Concluding that a patient has a infection based on measurement of an elevated body temperature and reported headache. Concluding that there were problems in an investigation because data from PCR and microarray are conflicting. Concluding that &apos;defects in gene XYZ cause cancer due to improper DNA repair&apos; based on data from experiments in that study that gene XYZ is involved in DNA repair, and the conclusion of a previous study that cancer patients have an increased number of mutations in this gene. 
Un processus planifié dans lequel les données recueillies sont évaluées dans le contexte des connaissances existantes dans le but de générer des conclusions plus générales ou de conclure que les données ne permettent pas de tirer une conclusion générale.
N&apos;est-ce pas un cas particulier de &quot;tirer une conclusion ?&quot;
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
drawing a conclusion based on data
Bjoern Peters
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Jennifer Fostel
Frank Gibson
Bill Bug
Melanie Courtot
Daniel Schober
light emission function
A light emission function is an excitation function to excite a material to a specific excitation state that it emits light.
Melanie Courtot
Frank Gibson
contain function
Daniel Schober
Bill Bug
A syringe, a beaker
A contain function is a function to constrain a material entities location in space
Jeaan-Marc Meunier
Une fonction de contenu est une fonction qui contraint une entité matériel dans une partie de l&apos;expace.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une fonction de filtrage est une fonction visant à retenir certaines entités en fonction de leur(s) qualités de l&apos;entité tout en permettant à des entités ayant des qualités différentes de passer.
filter function
A filter function is a function to prevent the flow of certain entities based on a quality or qualities of the entity while allowing entities which have different qualities to pass through
Frank Gibson
Melanie Courtot
Frank Gibson
Taped, glued, pinned, dried or molecularly bonded to a solid support
A solid support function is a function of a device on which an entity is kept in a defined position and prevented in its movement
Daniel Schober
solid support function
Bill Bug
An environmental control function is a function that regulates a contained environment within specified parameter ranges. For example the control of light exposure, humidity and temperature.
Frank Gibson
Melanie Courtot
Daniel Schober
environment control function
sort function
Frank Gibson
Melanie Courtot
A sort function is a function to distinguish material components based on some associated physical quality or entity and to partition the separate components into distinct fractions according to a defined order.
Daniel Schober
Jean-Marc Meunier

a vector role played by a small, self-replicating DNA or RNA molecule - usually a plasmid or chromosome - and realized in a process whereby foreign DNA or RNA is inserted into the vector during the process of cloning.

PERSON: Helen Parkinson
cloning vector role
pBluescript plays the role of a cloning vector
extracted material
an extract is a material entity which results from an extraction process
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
GROUP: OBI Biomatrial Branch
Up-regulation of inflammatory signalings by areca nut extract and role of cyclooxygenase-2 -1195G&gt;a polymorphism reveal risk of oral cancer. Cancer Res. 2008 Oct 15;68(20):8489-98. PMID: 18922923
extract
genotype profiling, SNP genotyping
genotyping assay
OBI Biomaterial
Philippe Rocca-Serra
High-throughput genotyping of oncogenic human papilloma viruses with MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry. Clin Chem. 2008 Jan;54(1):86-92. Epub 2007 Nov 2.PMID: 17981923
Jean-Marc Meunier
PPPB branch
PPPB branch
assay objective
Une objectif visant àdéterminer un type spécifié d&apos;informations sur une entitéévaluée.
an objective specification to determine a specified type of information about an evaluated entity (the material entity bearing evaluant role)
the objective to determine the weight of a mouse.
2013-09-23: simplify equivalent axiom
analyte assay
Note: is_realization of some analyte role isn&apos;t always true, for example when there is none of the analyte in the evaluant. For the moment we are writing it this way, but when the information ontology is further worked out this will be replaced with a condition discussing the measurement.
PERSON:Bjoern Peters, Helen Parkinson, Philippe Rocca-Serra, Alan Ruttenberg
An assay with the objective to capture information about the presence, concentration, or amount of an analyte in an evaluant.
example of usage: In lab test for blood glucose, the test is the assay, the blood bears evaluant_role and glucose bears the analyte role. The evaluant is considered an input to the assay and the information entity that records the measurement of glucose concentration the output
target of material addition role
peritoneum of an animal receiving an interperitoneal injection; solution in a tube receiving additional material; location of absorbed material following a dermal application.
target of material addition role is a role realized by an entity into which a material is added in a material addition process
OBI
GROUP:Role Branch
From Branch discussion with BP, AR, MC -- there is a need for the recipient to interact with the administered material.for example, a tooth receiving a filling was not considered to be a target role.
PERSON: Helen Parkinson
Jean-Marc Meunier
A glucometer measures blood glucose concentration, the glucometer has a measure function.
La fonction de mesure est une fonction qui est supportée par un matériau traité et réalisée dans un processus dans lequel des informations sur une entité sont exprimées par rapport à une référence.
Measure function is a function that is borne by a processed materialand realized in a process in which information about some entity is expressed relative to some reference.
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
PERSON:Frank Gibson
PERSON: Daniel Schober
measure function
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
artifactcreation objective
an objective specifiction that creates an specific output object from input materials.
PERSON: Frank Gibson
The objective to create a mouse infected with LCM virus. The objective to create a defined solution of PBS.
PERSON: Jennifer Fostel
GROUP: OBI PlanAndPlannedProcess Branch
material transformation objective
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
injecting a mouse with PBS solution, weighing it, and recording the weight according to a study design.
6/11/9: edited at workshop. Used to be: study design execution is a process with the objective to generate data according to a concretized study design. The execution of a study design is part of an investigation, and minimally consists of an assay or data transformation.
a planned process that realizes the concretization of a study design
Jean-Marc Meunier
removed axiom has_part some (assay or &apos;data transformation&apos;) per discussion on protocol application mailing list to improve reasoner performance. The axiom is still desired.
study design execution
branch derived
DNA sequencing is a sequencing process which uses deoxyribonucleic acid as input and results in a the creation of DNA sequence information artifact using a DNA sequencer instrument.
OBI Branch derived
Philippe Rocca-Serra
DNA sequencing
Genomic deletions of OFD1 account for 23% of oral-facial-digital type 1 syndrome after negative DNA sequencing. Thauvin-Robinet C, Franco B, Saugier-Veber P, Aral B, Gigot N, Donzel A, Van Maldergem L, Bieth E, Layet V, Mathieu M, Teebi A, Lespinasse J, Callier P, Mugneret F, Masurel-Paulet A, Gautier E, Huet F, Teyssier JR, Tosi M, Frébourg T, Faivre L.Hum Mutat. 2008 Nov 19. PMID: 19023858
bp
is a material processing with the objective to combine two or more material entities as input into a single material entity as output.
bp
created at workshop as parent class for &apos;adding material into target&apos;, which is asymmetric, while combination encompasses all addition processes.
material combination
Mixing two fluids. Adding salt into water. Injecting a mouse with PBS.
Philly2013: A specimen collection can have as part a material entity acquisition, such as ordering from a bank. The distinction is that specimen collection necessarily involves the creation of a specimen role. However ordering cell lines cells from ATCC for use in an investigation is NOT a specimen collection, because the cell lines already have a specimen role.
Note: definition is in specimen creation objective which is defined as an objective to obtain and store a material entity for potential use as an input during an investigation.
6/9/09: used at workshop
A planned process with the objective of collecting a specimen.
Philly2013: The specimen_role for the specimen is created during the specimen collection process.
drawing blood from a patient for analysis, collecting a piece of a plant for depositing in a herbarium, buying meat from a butcher in order to measure its protein content in an investigation
Bjoern Peters
5/31/2012: This process is not necessarily an acquisition, as specimens may be collected from materials already in posession
specimen collection
PERSON: Monnie McGee
error corrected data set
Un ensemble de donnéesrésultant d&apos;une transformation de données avec l&apos;objectif de correction d&apos;erreur etqui consiste à produire un ensemble de données ayant des contributions erronées en entréeet quela transformation a supprimées.
PERSON: James Malone
Jean-Marc Meunier
A data set that is produced as the output of an error correction data transformation and consists of producing a data set which has had erroneous contributions from the input to the data transformation removed (corrected for).
we need to work on this: Is taking a urine sample a material separation process? If not, we will need to specify what &apos;taking a sample from organism&apos; entails. We can argue that the objective to obtain a urine sample from a patient is enough to call it a material separation process, but it could dilute what material separation was supposed to be about.
sample from organism
5/29: This is a helper class for now
a material obtained from an organism in order to be a representative of the whole
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
statistical hypothesis test
James Malone
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Un test statistique fournit un mécanisme de décision quantitative concernant unou des processus
PERSON: James Malone
&quot;A statistical test provides a mechanism for making quantitative decisions about a process or processes&quot;.
http://www.itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/prc/section1/prc13.htm
Jean-Marc Meunier
A statistical hypothesis test data transformation is a data transformation that has objective statistical hypothesis test.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
center value
median
PRS and AGB added restriction about &apos;measure of central tendency&apos; and quartile, june 2013
A Dictionary of Statistical Terms, 5th edition, prepared for the International Statistical Institute by F.H.C. Marriott. Published for the International Statistical Institute by Lo



Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%A9diane_(statistiques)
PERSON: Monnie McGee
A data item that is produced as the output of a center calculation data transformation and represents the center value of the input data.
PERSON: James Malone
En théorie des probabilités et en statistiques, la médiane d&apos;un ensemble de valeurs (échantillon, population, distribution de probabilités) est une valeur m qui permet de couper l&apos;ensemble des valeurs en deux parties égales : mettant d&apos;un côté une moitié des valeurs, qui sont toutes inférieures ou égales à m et de l&apos;autre côté l&apos;autre moitié des valeurs, qui sont toutes supérieures ou égales à m (s&apos;il y a un nombre impair de valeurs, la valeur centrale sera mise des deux côtés). Intuitivement, on peut dire que la médiane est le point milieu de l&apos;ensemble1, qu&apos;elle divise en deux moitiés. C&apos;est une caractéristique de position de la série. On peut déterminer une médiane pour un ensemble de valeurs non numériques1 pour autant qu&apos;on puisse choisir un critère d&apos;ordonnancement de ces valeurs.
second quartile
Jean-Marc Meunier
Person:Helen Parkinson
James Malone
hypothesis test objective
is a data transformation objective where the aim is to estimate statistical significance with the aim of proving or disproving a hypothesis by means of some data transformation 
statistical hypothesis test objective
C&apos;est un objectif de transformation de données dans lequel l&apos;objectif est d&apos;estimer la signification statistique dans le but de prouver ou de réfuter une hypothèse au moyen d&apos;une transformation de données.
Jean-Marc Meunier
WEB:http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_hypothesis_testing
separation into different composition objective
A material separation objective aiming to separate a material entity that has parts of different types, and end with at least one output that is a material with parts of fewer types (modulo impurities).
We should be using has the grain relations or concentrations to distinguish the portioning and other sub-objectives
The objective to obtain cells contained in a sample of blood.
specimen collection objective
The objective to collect bits of excrement in the rainforest. The objective to obtain a blood sample from a patient.
A objective specification to obtain a material entity for potential use as an input during an investigation.
Bjoern Peters
Bjoern Peters
A recombinant vector is created by a recombinant vector cloning process, and contains nucleic acids that can be amplified. It retains functions of the original cloning vector.
recombinant vector
A cloning vector is an engineered material that is used as an input material for a recombinant vector cloning process to carry inserted nucleic acids. It contains an origin of replication for a specific destination host organism, encodes for a selectable gene product and contains a cloning site.
cloning vector
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-test
Le test de Student, ou test t, est un ensemble de tests d’hypothèse paramétriques où la statistique calculée suit une loi de Student lorsque l’hypothèse nulle est vraie. Un test de Student peut être utilisé notamment pour tester statistiquement l’hypothèse d’égalité de l&apos;espérance de deux variables aléatoires suivant une loi normale et de variance inconnue. Il est aussi très souvent utilisé pour tester la nullité d&apos;un coefficient dans le cadre d&apos;une régression linéaire. Il est utilisé pour déterminer si deux ensembles de données sont significativement différents l&apos;un de l&apos;autre.
t-test
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
James Malone
Jean-Marc Meunier
Studen&apos;t t-test is a data transformation with the objective of a statistical hypothesis test in which the test statistic has a Student&apos;s t distribution if the null hypothesis is true. It is applied when the population is assumed to be normally distributed but the sample sizes are small enough that the statistic on which inference is based is not normally distributed because it relies on an uncertain estimate of standard deviation rather than on a precisely known value.
Student&apos;s t-test
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_de_Student
A specimen gathering process with the objective to obtain a specimen that is representative of the input material entity
material sampling process
Jean-Marc Meunier
Web: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependent_and_independent_variables
Unedirective qui fait partie d&apos;un plan d&apos;étude . Les variables indépendantes sont des entités dont les valeurs sont sélectionnées pour déterminer leur relation avec un phénomène observé (la variable dépendante).
2009-03-16: work has been done on this term during during the OBI workshop winter 2009 and the current definition was considered acceptable for use in OBI. If there is a need to modify thisdefinition please notify OBI.
a directive information entity that is part of a study design. Independent variables are entities whose values are selected to determine its relationship to an observed phenomenon (the dependent variable). In such an experiment, an attempt is made to find evidence that the values of the independent variable determine the values of the dependent variable (that which is being measured). The independent variable can be changed as required, and its values do not represent a problem requiring explanation in an analysis, but are taken simply as given. The dependent variable on the other hand, usually cannot be directly controlled
study design independent variable
2/2/2009 Original definition - In the design of experiments, independent variables are those whose values are controlled or selected by the person experimenting (experimenter) to determine its relationship to an observed phenomenon (the dependent variable). In such an experiment, an attempt is made to find evidence that the values of the independent variable determine the values of the dependent variable (that which is being measured). The independent variable can be changed as required, and its values do not represent a problem requiring explanation in an analysis, but are taken simply as given. The dependent variable on the other hand, usually cannot be directly controlled.
Facteur expérimental
PERSON: Chris Stoeckert
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
experimental factor
independent variable
In the Philly 2013 workshop the label was chosen to distinguish it from &quot;dependent variable&quot; as used in statistical modelling. See: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_modeling
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
In a study in which gene expression is measured in patients between 8 month to 4 years old that have mild or severe malaria and in which the hypothesis is that gene expression in that age group is a function of disease status, disease status is the independent variable.
dependent variable
dependent variable specification is part of a study design. The dependent variable is the event studied and expected to change when the independent variable varies.
Jean-Marc Meunier
study design dependent variable
PRS-AGB: a dependent variable is a variable which assumes only values set by the operator according to a plan and are expected to influence the ranges of values assumed by a response variable aka independent variable.
PERSON: Chris Stoeckert
2009-03-16: work has been done on this term during during the OBI workshop winter 2009 and the current definition was considered acceptable for use in OBI. If there is a need to modify thisdefinition please notify OBI.
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
2/2/2009 In the design of experiments, independent variables are those whose values are controlled or selected by the person experimenting (experimenter) to determine its relationship to an observed phenomenon (the dependent variable). In such an experiment, an attempt is made to find evidence that the values of the independent variable determine the values of the dependent variable (that which is being measured). The independent variable can be changed as required, and its values do not represent a problem requiring explanation in an analysis, but are taken simply as given. The dependent variable on the other hand, usually cannot be directly controlled.
La spécification variable dépendante fait partie d&apos;un plan d&apos;étude. La variable dépendante est l&apos;événement étudié et quidevrait changer lorsque la variable indépendante varie.
In a study in which gene expression is measured in patients between 8 month to 4 years old that have mild or severe malaria and in which the hypothesis is that gene expression in that age group is a function of disease status, the gene expression is the dependent variable. 
In the Philly 2013 workshop the label was chosen to distinguish it from &quot;dependent variable&quot; as used in statistical modelling. See: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_modeling
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependent_and_independent_variables
PERSON: Alan Ruttenberg
A measurement data that represents the percentage of people or animals in a study or treatment group who are alive for a given period of time after diagnosis or initiation of monitoring.
Oliver He
survival rate
Une donnée qui représente le pourcentage de personnes ou d&apos;animaux dans un groupe d&apos;étude ou de traitement qui sont en vie pendant une période donnée après le diagnostic ou l&apos;initiation du suivi.
Jean-Marc Meunier
multiple comparison correction objective
Un objectif de correction de test multiple est un objectif de transformation de données dans lequel l&apos;objectif est de corriger un ensemble d&apos;inférences statistiques considérées simultanément.
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_Testing_Correction
Application of the Bonferroni correction
A multiple testing correction objectives is a data transformation objective where the aim is to correct for a set of statistical inferences considered simultaneously
Jean-Marc Meunier
multiple testing correction objective
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
C&apos;est une spécification d&apos;objectif visant lemaintien decertaines ou toutes les qualités d&apos;un matériel au fil du temps.
material maintenance objective
An objective specification maintains some or all of the qualities of a material over time.
placeholder for SO
a quality of a DNA molecule that inheres in its bearer due to the order of its DNA nucleotide residues.
BP et al
primary structure of DNA macromolecule
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzales-Beltran
Tina Boussard
Likelihood-ratio test
Le test du rapport de vraisemblance est un test statistique qui évalue la qualité de l&apos;ajustement entre deux modèles et s&apos;il existe des indices de la nécessité de passer d&apos;un modèle simple à un modèle plus compliqué (où le modèle simple est imbriqué dans le complexe) .
Likelihood-ratio test is a statistical test which evaluates the goodness-of-fit between two models and whether there is evidence of the need to move from a simple model to a more complicated one (where the simple model is nested within the complicated one)


A survival curve is a report graph which is a graphical representation of data where the percentage of survival is plotted as a function of time.
Une courbe de survie est un graphique une représentation des données où le pourcentage de survie est tracé en fonction du temps.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
PERSON:James Malone
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
PERSON:Melanie Courtot
WEB: http://www.graphpad.com/www/book/survive.htm
survival curve
PERSON:Chris Stoeckert
Bjoern Peters
Jean-Marc Meunier
nominal mesurement datum
categorical measurement datum
A measurement datum that is reported on a categorical scale
Une mesure sur une échelle catégorielle
in live cell assay
An assay in which a measurement is made by observing entities located in a live cell.
A voltmeter is a measurement device which is intended to perform some measure function.
A material entity that is designed to perform a function in a scientific investigation, but is not a reagent.
PERSON: Helen Parkinson
device
An autoclave is a device that sterlizes instruments or contaminated waste by applying high temperature and pressure.
OBI development call 2012-12-17.
instrument
nucleic acid extract
UPenn Group
An extract that is the output of an extraction process in which nucleic acid molecules are isolated from a specimen.
PERSON: Jie Zheng
labeled nucleic acid extract
a labeled specimen that is the output of a labeling process and has grain labeled nucleic acid for detection of the nucleic acid in future experiments.
labeled extract
MO_221 labeledExtract
Person: Jie Zheng
Jean-Marc Meunier
A data item of paired values, one indicating the dose of a material, the other quantitating a measured effect at that dose. The dosing intervals are chosen so that effect values be interpolated by a plotting a curve. 
Philippe Rocca-Serra, Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Bjoern Peters; Randi Vita
dose response curve
Un support de données composé de valeurs appariées, l&apos;une indiquant la dose d&apos;un produit, l&apos;autre quantifiant un effet mesuré en réponse à cette dose. Les intervalles de dosage sont choisis de sorte que les valeurs d&apos;effet soient interpolées par un tracé d&apos;une courbe.
Une valeur de confiance quantitative résultant d&apos;une méthode de correction d&apos;erreur de test multiple qui ajuste la valeur p utilisée comme entrée pour contrôler l&apos;erreur de type I dans le contexte de plusieurs tests par paires.
adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Familywise_error_rate) 
A quantitative confidence value resulting from a multiple testing error correction method which adjusts the p-value used as input to control for Type I error in the context of multiple pairwise tests
PERS:Philippe Rocca-Serra
FWER adjusted p-value
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://ugrad.stat.ubc.ca/R/library/LPE/html/mt.rawp2adjp.html
Addition of restriction &apos;output of null hypothesis testing&apos; and specified output by AGB and PRS while working on STATO
An assay in which sequencing technology (e.g. Solexa/454) is used to generate RNA sequence, analyse the transcibed regions of the genome, and or to quantitate transcript abundance
JZ: should be inferred as &apos;DNA sequencing&apos;. Will check in the future.
transcription profiling by high throughput sequencing
EFO_0002770 transcription profiling by high throughput sequencing
PERSON: James Malone
RNA-seq assay
discussed on San Diego OBI workshop, March 2011
Group: OBI group
Genotype information can be: Mus musculus wild type (in this case the genetic population background information is Mus musculus), C57BL/6JHnf1a+/- (in this case, C57BL/6J is the genetic population background information and Hnf1a+/- is the allele information
a genetic characteristics information that is about the genetic material of an organism and minimally includes information about the genetic background and can in addition contain information about specific alleles, genetic modifications, etc.
Group: OBI group
genotype information
A molecular feature identification objective that aims to characterize the abundance of transcripts
Group: Penn Group
Person: Chris Stoeckert, Jie Zheng
transcription profiling identification objective
MO_66 IndividualGeneticCharacteristics
Person: Chris Stoeckert, Jie Zheng
a data item that is about genetic material including polymorphisms, disease alleles, and haplotypes.
genetic characteristics information
Une valeur Q est une valeur p qui a été ajustée pour le taux de découverte fausse (FDR). Le False Discovery Rate est la proportion de faux positifs que vous pouvez espérer obtenir d&apos;un test. Une valeur p vous donne la probabilité d&apos;un faux positif sur un seul test; Si vous exécutez des centaines ou des milliers de tests à partir de petits échantillons (ce qui est commun dans des domaines comme la génomique), vous devez utiliser des valeurs de q.
PERS:Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://www.statisticshowto.com/q-value/
Addition of restriction &apos;output of null hypothesis testing&apos; by AGB and PRS while working on STATO
q-value
A Q-value is a p-value that has been adjusted for the False Discovery Rate(FDR). The False Discovery Rate is the proportion of false positives you can expect to get from a test. A p-value gives you the probability of a false positive on a single test; If you’re running hundreds or thousands of tests from small samples (which are common in fields like genomics), you should use q-values.
FDR adjusted p-value
A study design that classifies an individual or group of individuals on the basis of alleles, haplotypes, SNPs.
Jean-Marc Meunier
MO_560 genotyping_design
Person: Chris Stoeckert, Jie Zheng
genotyping design
Une conception d&apos;étude qui classe un individu ou un groupe d&apos;individus sur la base d&apos;allèles, haplotypes.
The part of a FASTA file that contains the letters ACTGGGAA 
8/29/11 call: This is added after a request from Melanie and Yu. They should review it further. This should be a child of &apos;sequence data&apos;, and as of the current definition will infer there.
DNA sequence data
OBI call; Bjoern Peters
A sequence data item that is about the primary structure of DNA
OBI call; Melanie Courtout
drawing a conclusion
Jean-Marc Meunier
A planned process in which new information is inferred from existing information.
Un processus planifier dans lequel de nouvelles informations sont inférées d&apos;informations existantes.
Penn Group
A device made to be used in an analyte assay for immobilization of substances that bind the analyte at regular spatial positions on a surface.
assay array
PERSON: Chris Stoeckert, Jie Zheng, Alan Ruttenberg
In the Philly 2013 workshop, we recognized the limitations of &quot;conclusion textual entity&quot;, and we introduced this as more general. The need for the &apos;textual entity&apos; term going forward is up for future debate. 
conclusion based on data
Une entité support d&apos;information qui est déduite des données
Jean-Marc Meunier
Group:2013 Philly Workshop group
Group:2013 Philly Workshop group
An information content entity that is inferred from data.
A value specification that is specifies one category out of a fixed number of nominal categories
Contrairement à la spécification de caleur scalaire, la définition pour les valeur catégorielle n&apos;évoque pas l&apos;association avec une unité.Oubli ou changement de point de vue ?
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON:Bjoern Peters
Une spécification de valeur qui permet de spécifier une catégorie parmi un ensemble connu de catégorie nominale
PERSON:Bjoern Peters
Une spécification de valeur constituée de deux partie un nombre et une étiquette d&apos;unité.
scalar value specification
A value specification that consists of two parts: a numeral and a unit label
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON:Bjoern Peters
Une entité de support d&apos;information qui spécifie une valeur dans un schéma de classification ou à une échelle quantitative.
value specification
The value of &apos;positive&apos; in a classification scheme of &quot;positive or negative&quot;; the value of &apos;20g&apos; on the quantitative scale of mass.
An information content entity that specifies a value within a classification scheme or on a quantitative scale.
This term is currently a descendant of &apos;information content entity&apos;, which requires that it &apos;is about&apos; something. A value specification of &apos;20g&apos; for a measurement data item of the mass of a particular mouse &apos;is about&apos; the mass of that mouse. However there are cases where a value specification is not clearly about any particular. In the future we may change &apos;value specification&apos; to remove the &apos;is about&apos; requirement.
molecular-labeled material
PERSON:Matthew Brush
OBI developer call, 3-12-12
a material entity that is the specified output of an addition of molecular label process that aims to label some molecular target to allow for its detection in a detection of molecular label assay
organism
A material entity that is an individual living system, such as animal, plant, bacteria or virus, that is capable of replicating or reproducing, growth and maintenance in the right environment. An organism may be unicellular or made up, like humans, of many billions of cells divided into specialized tissues and organs.
plant
GROUP: OBI Biomaterial Branch
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organism
virus
10/21/09: This is a placeholder term, that should ideally be imported from the NCBI taxonomy, but the high level hierarchy there does not suit our needs (includes plasmids and &apos;other organisms&apos;)
fungus
animal
A material entity that has the specimen role.
Note: definition is in specimen creation objective which is defined as an objective to obtain and store a material entity for potential use as an input during an investigation.
GROUP: OBI Biomaterial Branch
PERSON: James Malone
Biobanking of blood taken and stored in a freezer for potential future investigations stores specimen.
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
specimen
The extent of a &apos;cultured cell population&apos; is restricted only in that all cell members must share a propagation history (ie be derived through a common lineage of passages from an initial culture). In being defined in this way, this class can be used to refer to the populations that researchers actually use in the practice of science - ie are the inputs to culturing, experimentation, and sharing. The cells in such populations will be a relatively uniform population as they have experienced similar selective pressures due to their continuous co-propagation. And this population will also have a single passage number, again owing to their common passaging history. Cultured cell populations represent only a collection of cells (ie do not include media, culture dishes, etc), and include populations of cultured unicellular organisms or cultured multicellular organism cells. They can exist under active culture, stored in a quiescent state for future use, or applied experimentally.
A processed material comprised of a collection of cultured cells that has been continuously maintained together in culture and shares a common propagation history.
2013-6-5 MHB: This OBI class was formerly called &apos;cell culture&apos;, but label changed and definition updated following CLO alignment efforts in spring 2013, during which the intent of this class was clarified to refer to portions of a culture or line rather than a complete cell culture or line.
PERSON:Matthew Brush
cell culture sample
PERSON:Matthew Brush
cultured cell population
data transformation
Elisabetta Manduchi
Tina Hernandez-Boussard
Ryan Brinkman
James Malone
data processing
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Branch editors
A planned process that produces output data from input data.
Helen Parkinson
Jean-Marc Meunier
Melanie Courtot
Richard Scheuermann
The application of a clustering protocol to microarray data or the application of a statistical testing method on a primary data set to determine a p-value.
Un processus planifié qui produit des données de sortie à partir de données d&apos;entrée.
data analysis
Benjamini and Hochberg false discovery rate correction method
A data transformation process in which the Benjamini and Hochberg method sequential p-value procedureis applied with the aim of correcting false discovery rate
Statistical significance of the 8 most represented biological processes (GO level 4) among E7 6 month upregulated genes following analysis with DAVID software; Benjamini-Hochberg FDR (false discovery rate)
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
cette procédure fait en sorte que les p-values augmentent en fonction de leur nombre et du taux de p-values non-significatives. Elle fait partie de la famille de correction type FDR (False Discovery Rate). Etant peu conservatrice ( = peu sévère), elle est bien adaptée aux situations où l’on cherche à sélectionner un grand nombre de caractères potentiellement intéressants. Elle est très souvent utilisée dans les problématiques 

https://www.xlstat.com/fr/solutions/fonctionnalites/differential-expression
Helen Parkinson
Helen Parkinson
A data transformation in which the Benjamini and Yekutieli method is applied with the aim of correcting false discovery rate
cette procédure fait en sorte que les p-values augmentent en fonction de leur nombre et du taux de p-values non-significatives. Elle fait partie de la famille de correction type FDR (False Discovery Rate). En plus de la procédure de Benjamini-Hochberg, elle prend en compte une possible dépendance entre les éléments testés. Elle est par conséquent un peu plus conservatrice que la procédure précédente mais beaucoup

Benjamini and Yekutieli false discovery rate correction method
Jean-Marc Meunier
https://www.xlstat.com/fr/solutions/fonctionnalites/differential-expression
The expression set was compared univariately between the stroke patients and controls, gene list was generated using False Discovery Rate correction (Benjamini and Yekutieli)
Helen Parkinson
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Person:Helen Parkinson
t-tests were used with the type I error adjusted for multiple comparisons, Holm&apos;s correction (HOLM 1979), and false discovery rate, http://www.genetics.org/cgi/content/full/172/2/1179
Lorsque vous réalisez de multiples tests de significativité statistique sur les mêmes données, l&apos;ajustement de Bonferroni peut être appliqué pour qu&apos;il soit plus &quot;difficile&quot; à ces tests d&apos;être statistiquement significatifs. Par exemple, lorsque vous étudiez les coefficients de corrélation multiple d&apos;une matrice de corrélation, il peut être inapproprié d&apos;accepter et d&apos;interpréter les corrélations statistiquement significatives au niveau 0,05, étant donné que vous effectuez de multiples tests. Précisément, c&apos;est la probabilité d&apos;erreur alpha d&apos;accepter en se trompant le coefficient de corrélation observé comme non-égal-à-zéro alors que le fait (dans la population) qu&apos;il soit égal à zéro peut être 

http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/a/bonferroni.html
Holm-Bonferroni family-wise error rate correction method
a data transformation that performs more than one hypothesis test simultaneously, a closed-test procedure, thatcontrols the familywise error rate for all the k hypotheses at level α in the strong sense. Objective: multiple testing correction
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holm%E2%80%93Bonferroni_method
Correstion de Bonferroni
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Monnie McGee
Traduction à vérifier
A family wise error rate correction method is a multiple testing procedure that controls the probability of at least one false positive.
Dudoit, Sandrine and van der Laan, Mark J. (2008) Multiple Testing Procedures with Applications to Genomics.New York: Springer , p. 19
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Laméthode de correction de taux d&apos;erreur familiale prudente est une procédure de test multiple qui contrôle la probabilité d&apos;au moins un faux positif.
Jean-Marc Meunier
family wise error rate correction method
FWER correction
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
A descriptive statistical calculation objective is a data transformation objective which concerns any calculation intended to describe a feature of a data set, for example, its center or its variability.
Un objectif de calcul statistique descriptif est un objectif de transformation de données qui concerne tout calcul destiné à décrire une caractéristique d&apos;un ensemble de données, par exemple son centre ou sa variabilité.
PERSON: James Malone
Elisabetta Manduchi
PERSON: Monnie McGee
James Malone
descriptive statistical calculation objective
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: Elisabetta Manduchi
Jean-Marc Meunier
Monnie McGee
Melanie Courtot
Une transformation logarithmique est une transformation de données consistant en l&apos;application de la fonction de logarithme avec une base donnée a (où a&gt; 0 et a n&apos;est pas égal à 1) à une entrée de nombre réel positive (une dimension). La fonction de logarithme avec base a peut être définie comme l&apos;inverse de la fonction exponentielle avec la même base.
logarithmic transformation
WEB: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logarithm
Elisabetta Manduchi
Jean-Marc Meunier
A logarithmic transformation is a data transformation consisting in the application of the logarithm function with a given base a (where a&gt;0 and a is not equal to 1) to a (one dimensional) positive real number input. The logarithm function with base a can be defined as the inverse of the exponential function with the same base. See e.g. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logarithm.
PERSON: James Malone
Elisabetta Manduchi
PERSON: Melanie Courtot
visualization
Processus plannifié qui crée des images, diagrammes ou animations à partir de données d&apos;entrée.
data encoding as image
PERSON: Elisabetta Manduchi
James Malone
Tina Boussard
data visualization
An planned process that creates images, diagrams or animations from the input data.
PERSON: Tina Boussard
Jean-Marc Meunier
Est-ce queles diagrammes ne devrait pas être sous cette classe ?
Melanie Courtot
Generation of a heatmap from a microarray dataset
Un calcul de mode est un calcul de statistiques descriptives dans lequel le mode est calculé. il correspond à la valeur la plus fréquente dans un ensemble de données. Il est le plus souvent utilisé comme mesure de tendance centrale pour des données discrètes.
A mode calculation is a descriptive statistics calculation in which the mode is calculated which is the most common value in a data set. It is most often used as a measure of center for discrete data.
Monnie McGee
Jean-Marc Meunier
James Malone
From Monnie&apos;s file comments - need to add center_calculation role but it doesn&apos;t exist yet - (editor note added by James Jan 2008)
mode calculation
PERSON: Monnie McGee
La définition n&apos;est pas applicable aux données catégorielles qui ne peuvent avoir de centre faute d&apos;être ordonnées
PERSON: James Malone
Jean-Marc Meunier
A median calculation is adescriptive statistics calculation in which the midpoint of the data set (the 0.5 quantile) is calculated.First, the observations are sorted in increasing order.For an odd number of observations, the median is the middle value of the sorted data.For an even number of observations, the median is the average of the two middle values.
Un calcul médian est un calcul de statistiques descriptives dans lequel le point médian de l&apos;ensemble de données (le quantile 0,5) est calculé. Tout d&apos;abord, les observations sont triées en ordre croissant. Pour un nombre impair d&apos;observations, la médiane est la valeur moyenne des données triées. Pour un nombre pair d&apos;observations, la médiane est la moyenne des deux valeurs du milieu.
Monnie McGee
median calculation
From Monnie&apos;s file comments - need to add center_calculation role but it doesn&apos;t exist yet - (editor note added by James Jan 2008)
James Malone
PERSON: Monnie McGee
PERSON: James Malone
Dudoit, Sandrine and van der Laan, Mark J. (2008) Multiple Testing Procedures with Applications to Genomics.New York: Springer , p. 21 and http://www.wikidoc.org/index.php/False_discovery_rate
The false discovery rate is adata transformation used in multiple hypothesis testing to correct for multiple comparisons. It controls the expected proportion of incorrectly rejected null hypotheses (type I errors) in a list of rejected hypotheses. It is a less conservative comparison procedure with greater power than familywise error rate (FWER) control, at a cost of increasing the likelihood of obtaining type I errors. .
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
La correctin du taux de fauses découverteest une transformation de données utilisée dans les tests d&apos;hypothèses multiples pour corriger les comparaisons multiples. Il contrôle la proportion attendue d&apos;hypothèses nulles incorrectement rejetées (erreurs de type I) dans une liste d&apos;hypothèses rejetées. C&apos;est une procédure de comparaison moins conservatrice avec une plus grande puissance que le FWER.
FDR correction method
Monnie McGee
false discovery rate correction method
Jean-Marc Meunier
PERSON: James Malone
Elisabetta Manduchi
James Malone
PERSON: Helen Parkinson
data normalization objective
Quantile transformation which has normalization objective can be used for expression microarray assay normalization and it is referred to as &quot;quantile normalization&quot;, according to the procedure described e.g. in PMID 12538238.
Objectif de transformation de données permettant d&apos;obtenir en sortie des données normalement distribuée.
PERSON: Elisabetta Manduchi
Helen Parkinson
normalization data transformation
Jean-Marc Meunier
James Malone
PERSON: James Malone
A normalization data transformation is a data transformation that has objective normalization.
En statistiques, la normalisation désigne la transformation d&apos;une série de valeurs pour qu&apos;elles se conforment à une distribu

http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/n/normalisation.html
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_exact_de_Fisher
James Malone
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le Test exact de Fisher est un test statistique utilisé pour l&apos;analyse des tables de contingence. Ce test est utilisé en général avec des faibles effectifs mais il est valide pour toutes les tailles d&apos;échantillon. Il doit son nom à son inventeur Ronald Fisher. C&apos;est un test qualifié d&apos;exact car les probabilités peuvent être calculées exactement plutôt qu&apos;en s&apos;appuyant sur une approximation qui ne devient correcte qu&apos;asymptotiquement comme pour le test du chi^2utilisé 

WEB:http://mathworld.wolfram.com/FishersExactTest.html
Fisher&apos;s exact test
Fisher&apos;s exact test is a data transformation used to determine if there are nonrandom associations between two Fisher&apos;s exact test is a statistical significance test used in the analysis of contingency tables where sample sizes are small where the significance of the deviation from a null hypothesis can be calculated exactly, rather than relying on an approximation that becomes exact in the limit as the sample size grows to infinity, as with many statistical tests.
gene list visualization
James Malone
Adata visualization which has input of a gene list and produces an output of a report graph which is capable of rendering data of this type.
The chi-square test is a data transformation with the objective of statistical hypothesis testing, in which the sampling distribution of the test statistic is a chi-square distribution when the null hypothesis is true, or any in which this is asymptotically true, meaning that the sampling distribution (if the null hypothesis is true) can be made to approximate a chi-square distribution as closely as desired by making the sample size large enough.
PERSON: James Malone
Jean-Marc Meunier
negociation with OBI hence definition and definition source are missing from this class
chi square test
PERSON: Tina Boussard
Le test du chi-carré est une transformation de données ayant pour objectif un test d&apos;hypothèse statistique, dans lequel la distribution d&apos;échantillonnage de la statistique de test est une distribution chi-carré lorsque l&apos;hypothèse nulle est vraie ouelle est asymptotiquement vraie, ce qui signifie que la distribution d&apos;échantillonnage (si l&apos;hypothèse nulle est vraie) peut êtrerapprochée la distribution du chi-carré si lataille de l&apos;échantillon est suffisamment grande.
ANOVA
http://unt-ori2.crihan.fr/unspf/2010_Limoges_Vignoles_StatsAnova/co/09-1-1-introduction.html
Analysis of Variance
Jean-Marc Meunier
James Malone
Philippe Rocca-Serra
L&apos;analyse de la variance a pour but la comparaison des moyennes de k populations, à partir d&apos;échantillons aléatoires et indépendants préle

AGB and PRS augmented the class with formal definitions as part of STATO extension
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
ANOVA
ANalysis Of VAriance (ANOVA) is a data transformation in which a statistical test is performed to evaluate the null hypothesis that the means computed over the different groups as specified by the investigator do not differ. The test compares an F-statistics (a ratio of means) to an F-distribution and produces a p-value, used to reject or accept the null hypothesis given a false positive rate. The test assumes normality and equivariance of the data.
Person:Bjoern Peters
Philippe Rocca-Serra
A material separation in which a desired component of an input material is separated from the remainder
extraction
nucleic acid extraction using phenol chloroform
Jean-Marc Meunier
group randomization
Philippe Rocca-Serra
adapted from wikipedia [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randomization]
Une affectation de groupe qui repose sur le hasard pour attribuer des individus à un groupe afin d&apos;éviter les biaisexpérimentaux.
PMID: 18349405. Randomization reveals unexpected acute leukemias in Southwest Oncology Group prostate cancer trial. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Mar 20;26(9):1532-6.
A group assignment which relies on chance to assign materials to a group of materials in order to avoid bias in experimental set up.
flow_cell
Person:John Quinn
Biofilm Flow Cell
flow cell
http://www.flocyte.com/FRTP/Resources/flow_cytometry_glossary.htm
Aparatus in the fluidic subsystem where the sheath and sample meet. Can be one of several types; jet-in-air, quartz cuvette, or a hybrid of the two. The sample flows through the center of a fluid column of sheath fluid in the flow cell.
FACS Calibur
flow cytometer
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_cytometer
A flow_cytometer is an instrument for counting, examining and sorting microscopic particles in suspension. It allows simultaneous multiparametric analysis of the physical and/or chemical characteristics of single cells flowing through an optical and/or electronic detection apparatus. A flow cytometer is an instrument that can be used to quantitatively measure the properties of individual cells in a flowing medium.
John Quinn
Practical Flow Cytometry 4th Edition, Howard Shapiro, ISBN-10: 0471411256, ISBN-13: 978-0471411253
light source
John Quinn
A light source is an optical subsystem that provides light for use in a distant area using a delivery system (e.g., fiber optics). Light sources may include one of a variety of lamps (e.g., xenon, halogen, mercury). Most light sources are operated from line power, but some may be powered from batteries. They are mostly used in endoscopic, microscopic, and other examination and/or in surgical procedures. The light source is part of the optical subsystem. In a flow cytometer the light source directs high intensity light at particles at the interrogation point. The light source in a flow cytometer is usually a laser.
Olga Tchuvatkina
Elizabeth M. Goralczyk
Daniel Schober
obscuration bar in a flow cytometer
obscuration bar
John Quinn
An obscuration bar is a an optical subsystem which is a strip of metal or other material that serves to block out direct light from the illuminating beam. The obscuration bar prevents the bright light scattered in the forward directions from burning out the collection device.
Flow Cytometry: First Principles, by Alice Longobardi Givan, ISBN-10: 0471382248, ISBN-13: 978-0471382249
An optical filter is an optical subsystem that selectively transmits light having certain properties (often, a particular range of wavelengths, that is, range of colours of light), while blocking the remainder. They are commonly used in photography, in many optical instruments, and to colour stage lighting Optical filters can be arranged to segregate and collect light by wave length.
John Quinn
720 LP filter, 580/30 BP filter
optical filter
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical_filter
http://einstein.stanford.edu/content/glossary/glossary.html
A photomultiplier tube, a photo diode
John Quinn
photodetector
A photodetector is a device used to detect and measure the intensity of radiant energy through photoelectric action. In a cytometer, photodetectors measure either the number of photons of laser light scattered on impact with a cell (for example), or the flourescence emitted by excitation of a fluorescent dye.
Trish Whetzel
DNA sequencer
ABI 377 DNA Sequencer, ABI 310 DNA Sequencer
A DNA sequencer is an instrument that determines the order of deoxynucleotides in deoxyribonucleic acid sequences.
MO
Glass Array Hybridization Cassette
MO_563 hybridization_chamber
A device which is used to maintain constant contact of a liquid on an array.This can be either a glass vial or slide.
Trish Whetzel
hybridization chamber
cytometer
A cytometer is an instrument for counting and measuring cells.
http://medical.merriam-webster.com/medical/cytometer
Melanie Courtot
OBI Instrument branch
droplet sorter
OBI Instrument branch
PERSON: Chris Stoeckert
study design
C&apos;est une spécification de plan composée de protocoles (qui peut préciser comment et quels types de données seront recueillis) qui sont exécutés dans le cadre d&apos;une enquête et qui se réalisent lors d&apos;une exécution de conception d&apos;étude.
A plan specification comprised of protocols (which may specify how and what kinds of data will be gathered) that are executed as part of an investigation and is realized during a study design execution.
experimental design
rediscussed at length (MC/JF/BP). 12/9/08). The definition was clarified to differentiate it from protocol.
a matched pairs study design describes criteria by which subjects are identified as pairs which then undergo the same protocols, and the data generated is analyzed by comparing the differences between the paired subjects, which constitute the results of the executed study design.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Editor note: there is at least an implicit restriction on the kind of data transformations that can be done based on the measured data available.
Jean-Marc Meunier
C&apos;est un plan àmesures répétées qui garantit que les unités expérimentales reçoivent, en séquence, le traitement (ou le contrôle), puis, après un intervalle de temps spécifié, passe au contrôle ( ou traitement). Dans cette conception, les individus (patients dans le contexte humain) servent à leur propre contrôle, et la randomisation peut être utilisée pour déterminer quel sujet reçoit le traitement oule contrôle.
(source: http://www.sbu.se/Filer/Content0/publikationer/1/literaturesearching_1993/glossary.html)
cross over design
a repeated measure design which ensures that experimental units receive, in sequence, the treatment (or the control), and then, after a specified time interval (aka *wash-out periods*), switch to the control (or treatment). In this design, subjects (patients in human context) serve as their own controls, and randomization may be used to determine the ordering which a subject receives the treatment and control
Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plan_d%27%C3%A9tude_crois%C3%A9
PMID: 17601993-Objective: HIV-infected patients with lipodystrophy (HIV-lipodystrophy) are insulin resistant and have elevated plasma free fatty acid (FFA) concentrations. We aimed to explore the mechanisms underlying FFA-induced insulin resistance in patients with HIV-lipodystrophy. Research Design and Methods: Using a randomized placebo-controlled cross-over design, we studied the effects of an overnight acipimox-induced suppression of FFA on glucose and FFA metabolism by using stable isotope labelled tracer techniques during basal conditions and a two-stage euglycemic, hyperinsulinemic clamp (20 mU insulin/m(2)/min; 50 mU insulin/m(2)/min) in nine patients with nondiabetic HIV-lipodystrophy. All patients received antiretroviral therapy. Biopsies from the vastus lateralis muscle were obtained during each stage of the clamp. Results: Acipimox treatment reduced basal FFA rate of appearance by 68.9% (52.6%-79.5%) and decreased plasma FFA concentration by 51.6 % (42.0%-58.9%), (both, P &lt; 0.0001). Endogenous glucose production was not influenced by acipimox. During the clamp the increase in glucose-uptake was significantly greater after acipimox treatment compared to placebo (acipimox: 26.85 (18.09-39.86) vs placebo: 20.30 (13.67-30.13) mumol/kg/min; P &lt; 0.01). Insulin increased phosphorylation of Akt (Thr(308)) and GSK-3beta (Ser(9)), decreased phosphorylation of glycogen synthase (GS) site 3a+b and increased GS-activity (I-form) in skeletal muscle (P &lt; 0.01). Acipimox decreased phosphorylation of GS (site 3a+b) (P &lt; 0.02) and increased GS-activity (P &lt; 0.01) in muscle. Conclusion: The present study provides direct evidence that suppression of lipolysis in patients with HIV-lipodystrophy improves insulin-stimulated peripheral glucose-uptake. The increased glucose-uptake may in part be explained by increased dephosphorylation of GS (site 3a+b) resulting in increased GS activity.
http://www.holah.karoo.net/experimentaldesigns.htm
Philippe Rocca-Serra
A matched pair design is a study design which use groups of individuals associated (hence matched) to each other based on a set of criteria, one member going to one treatment, the other member receiving the other treatment.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une plan à paires appariées est une plan d&apos;étude qui utilise des groupes d&apos;individus associés (par conséquent, correspondants) selon l&apos;ensemble des critères, un membre va à un traitement, l&apos;autre membre recevant l&apos;autre traitement
matched pairs design
PMID: 17288613-BSTRACT: BACKGROUND: Physicians in Canadian emergency departments (EDs) annually treat 185,000 alert and stable trauma victims who are at risk for cervical spine (C-spine) injury. However, only 0.9% of these patients have suffered a cervical spine fracture. Current use of radiography is not efficient. The Canadian C-Spine Rule is designed to allow physicians to be more selective and accurate in ordering C-spine radiography, and to rapidly clear the C-spine without the need for radiography in many patients. The goal of this phase III study is to evaluate the effectiveness of an active strategy to implement the Canadian C-Spine Rule into physician practice. Specific objectives are to: 1) determine clinical impact, 2) determine sustainability, 3) evaluate performance, and 4) conduct an economic evaluation. METHODS: We propose a matched-pair cluster design study that compares outcomes during three consecutive 12-months before, after, and decay periods at six pairs of intervention and control sites. These 12 hospital ED sites will be stratified as teaching or community hospitals, matched according to baseline C-spine radiography ordering rates, and then allocated within each pair to either intervention or control groups. During the after period at the intervention sites, simple and inexpensive strategies will be employed to actively implement the Canadian C-Spine Rule. The following outcomes will be assessed: 1) measures of clinical impact, 2) performance of the Canadian C-Spine Rule, and 3) economic measures. During the 12-month decay period, implementation strategies will continue, allowing us to evaluate the sustainability of the effect. We estimate a sample size of 4,800 patients in each period in order to have adequate power to evaluate the main outcomes. DISCUSSION: Phase I successfully derived the Canadian C-Spine Rule and phase II confirmed the accuracy and safety of the rule, hence, the potential for physicians to improve care. What remains unknown is the actual change in clinical behaviors that can be affected by implementation of the Canadian C-Spine Rule, and whether implementation can be achieved with simple and inexpensive measures. We believe that the Canadian C-Spine Rule has the potential to significantly reduce health care costs and improve the efficiency of patient flow in busy Canadian EDs.
A randomized complete block design is_a study design which assigns randomly treatments to block. The number of units per block equals the number of treatment so each block receives each treatment exactly once (hence the qualifier &apos;complete&apos;). The design was originally devised from field trials used in agronomy and agriculture. The analysis assumes that there is no interaction between block and treatment. The method was then used in other settings So The randomised complete block design is a design in which the subjects are matched according to a variable which the experimenter wishes to control. The subjects are put into groups (blocks) of the same size as the number of treatments. The members of each block are then randomly assigned to different treatment groups.
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://www.tufts.edu/~gdallal/ranblock.htm
randomized complete block design
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://www.stats.gla.ac.uk/steps/glossary/anova.html,(A researcher is carrying out a study of the effectiveness of four different skin creams for the treatment of a certain skin disease. He has eighty subjects and plans to divide them into 4 treatment groups of twenty subjects each. Using a randomised blocks&amp; design, the subjects are assessed and put in blocks of four according to how severe their skin condition is; the four most severe cases are the first block, the next four most severe cases are the second block, and so on to the twentieth block. The four &amp;members of each block are then randomly assigned, one to each of the four treatment groups. http://www.stats.gla.ac.uk/steps/glossary/anova.html#rbd))
C&apos;est un plan d&apos;étude qui attribue des traitements aléatoires pour bloquer les variables parasites. Le nombre d&apos;unités par bloc équivaut au nombre de traitement afin que chaque bloc reçoive chaque traitement exactement une fois (d&apos;où le qualificatif &apos;complet&apos;). Il a été initialement conçu à partir d&apos;essais sur le terrain utilisés dans l&apos;agronomie et l&apos;agriculture.L&apos;analyse suppose qu&apos;il n&apos;y a pas d&apos;interaction entre le bloc et le traitement.La méthode a ensuite été utilisée dans d&apos;autres paramètres. Les sujets sont placés en groupes (blocs) de la même taille que le nombre de traitements. Les membres de chaque bloc sont ensuite assignés au hasard à différents groupes de traitement.
latin square design
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
PMID: 17582121-Our objective was to examine the effects of dietary cation-anion difference (DCAD) with different concentrations of dietary crude protein (CP) on performance and acid-base status in early lactation cows. Six lactating Holstein cows averaging 44 d in milk were used in a 6 x 6 Latin square design with a 2 x 3 factorial arrangement of treatments: DCAD of -3, 22, or 47 milliequivalents (Na + K - Cl - S)/100 g of dry matter (DM), and 16 or 19% CP on a DM basis. Linear increases with DCAD occurred in DM intake, milk fat percentage, 4% fat-corrected milk production, milk true protein, milk lactose, and milk solids-not-fat. Milk production itself was unaffected by DCAD. Jugular venous blood pH, base excess and HCO3(-) concentration, and urine pH increased, but jugular venous blood Cl- concentration, urine titratable acidity, and net acid excretion decreased linearly with increasing DCAD. An elevated ratio of coccygeal venous plasma essential AA to nonessential AA with increasing DCAD indicated that N metabolism in the rumen was affected, probably resulting in more microbial protein flowing to the small intestine. Cows fed 16% CP had lower urea N in milk than cows fed 19% CP; the same was true for urea N in coccygeal venous plasma and urine. Dry matter intake, milk production, milk composition, and acid-base status did not differ between the 16 and 19% CP treatments. It was concluded that DCAD affected DM intake and performance of dairy cows in early lactation. Feeding 16% dietary CP to cows in early lactation, compared with 19% CP, maintained lactation performance while reducing urea N excretion in milk and urine.
Latin square design is_a study design which allows in its simpler form controlling 2 levels of nuisance variables (also known as blocking variables). The 2 nuisance factors are divided into a tabular grid with the property that each row and each column receive each treatment exactly once.
Adapted from: http://www.itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/pri/section3/pri3321.htm and
Un carré latin est un plan d&apos;étude qui permet dans sa forme plus simple de contrôler 2 niveaux de variables parasites (également appelées variables de blocage). Les 2 facteurs parasite sont divisés en une grille tabulaire avec la propriété que chaque rangée et chaque colonne reçoivent chaque traitement exactement une fois.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://www.spc.univ-lyon1.fr/polycop/plan%20factoriel.htm
factorial design
PMID: 17582121-Our objective was to examine the effects of dietary cation-anion difference (DCAD) with different concentrations of dietary crude protein (CP) on performance and acid-base status in early lactation cows. Six lactating Holstein cows averaging 44 d in milk were used in a 6 x 6 Latin square design with a 2 x 3 factorial arrangement of treatments: DCAD of -3, 22, or 47 milliequivalents (Na + K - Cl - S)/100 g of dry matter (DM), and 16 or 19% CP on a DM basis. Linear increases with DCAD occurred in DM intake, milk fat percentage, 4% fat-corrected milk production, milk true protein, milk lactose, and milk solids-not-fat. Milk production itself was unaffected by DCAD. Jugular venous blood pH, base excess and HCO3(-) concentration, and urine pH increased, but jugular venous blood Cl- concentration, urine titratable acidity, and net acid excretion decreased linearly with increasing DCAD. An elevated ratio of coccygeal venous plasma essential AA to nonessential AA with increasing DCAD indicated that N metabolism in the rumen was affected, probably resulting in more microbial protein flowing to the small intestine. Cows fed 16% CP had lower urea N in milk than cows fed 19% CP; the same was true for urea N in coccygeal venous plasma and urine. Dry matter intake, milk production, milk composition, and acid-base status did not differ between the 16 and 19% CP treatments. It was concluded that DCAD affected DM intake and performance of dairy cows in early lactation. Feeding 16% dietary CP to cows in early lactation, compared with 19% CP, maintained lactation performance while reducing urea N excretion in milk and urine.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le plan factoriel (« factorial design ») est un plan d’expérience qui répond à deux questions différentes avec le même essai. Il permet un gain de temps et une « économie en patients ». Pour atteindre correctement son but, il est nécessaire que les traitements n’interagissent pas entre eux. Autrement, le plan factoriel perd sa puissance et se retrouve dans l’impossibilité de répondre à aucune des deux questions.
http://www.stats.gla.ac.uk/steps/glossary/anova.html#facdes And from wikipedia (01/03/2007): http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Factorial_experiment)
factorial design is_a study design which is used to evaluate two or more factors simultaneously. The treatments are combinations of levels of the factors. The advantages of factorial designs over one-factor-at-a-time experiments is that they are more efficient and they allow interactions to be detected. In statistics, a factorial design experiment is an experiment whose design consists of two or more factors, each with discrete possible values or levels, and whose experimental units take on all possible combinations of these levels across all such factors. Such an experiment allows studying the effect of each factor on the response variable, as well as the effects of interactions between factors on the response variable.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Une plan factorielcomporte 2 facteurs expérimentaux (càd variables indépendantes) et 2 niveauxpar facteur expérimental.
PMID: 17561240-The present experiment evaluates the effects of intermittent exposure to a social stimulus on ethanol and water drinking in rats. Four groups of rats were arranged in a 2x2 factorial design with 2 levels of Social procedure (Intermittent Social vs Continuous Social) and 2 levels of sipper Liquid (Ethanol vs Water). Intermittent Social groups received 35 trials per session. Each trial consisted of the insertion of the sipper tube for 10 s followed by lifting of the guillotine door for 15 s. The guillotine door separated the experimental rat from the conspecific rat in the wire mesh cage during the 60 s inter-trial interval. The Continuous Social groups received similar procedures except that the guillotine door was raised during the entire duration of the session. For the Ethanol groups, the concentrations of ethanol in the sipper [3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, and 16% (vol/vol)] increased across sessions, while the Water groups received 0% ethanol (water) in the sipper throughout the experiment. Both Social procedures induced more intake of ethanol than water. The Intermittent Social procedure induced more ethanol intake at the two highest ethanol concentration blocks (10-12% and 14-16%) than the Continuous Social procedure, but this effect was not observed with water. Effects of social stimulation on ethanol drinking are discussed.
a factorial design which has 2 experimental factors (aka independent variables) and 2 factor levels per experimental factors
Jean-Marc Meunier
2x2 factorial design
PMID: 17561240
PERSON:Bjoern Peters
collecting specimen from organism
taking a sputum sample from a cancer patient, taking the spleen from a killed mouse, collecting a urine sample from a patient
IEDB
a process with the objective to obtain a material entity that was part of an organism for potential future use in an investigation
a material processing in which components of an input material become segregated in space
Using a cell sorter to separate a mixture of T cells into two fractions; one with surface receptor CD8 and the other lacking the receptor, or purification
material component separation
IEDB
Bjoern Peters
Assigning&apos; to be treated with active ingredient role&apos; to an organism during group assignment. The group is those organisms that have the same role in the context of an investigation
Philippe Rocca-Serra
group assignment is a process which has an organism as specified input and during which a role is assigned
L&apos;affectation de groupe est un processus qui a un organisme comme entrée spécifiée et pendant lequel un rôle est assigné.
study assignment
group assignment
Jean-Marc Meunier
cohort assignment
OBI Plan
maintaining cell culture
OBI branch derived
a protocol application in which cells are kept alive in a defined environment outside of an organism.part of cell_culturing
When harvesting blood from a human, isolating T cells, and then limited dilution cloning of the cells, the maintaining_cell_culture step comprises all steps after the initial dilution and plating of the cells into culture, e.g. placing the culture into an incubator, changing or adding media, and splitting a cell culture
PlanAndPlannedProcess Branch
A &apos;cell culture&apos; as used here referes to a new lineage of cells in culture deriving from a single biological source.. New cultures are established through the initial isolation and culturing of cells from an organismal source, or through changes in an existing cell culture or line that result in a new culture with unique characteristics.This can occur through the passaging/selection of a primary culture into a secondary culture or line, or experimental modifications of an existing cell culture or line such as an immortalization process or other stable genetic modification. This class covers establishment of cultures of either multicellular organism cells or unicellular organisms.
establishing cell culture
PERSON:Matthew Brush
PERSON:Matthew Brush
a process through which a new type of cell culture or cell line is created, either through the isolation and culture of one or more cells from a fresh source, or the deliberate experimental modification of an existing cell culture (e.g passaging a primary culture to become a secondary culture or line, or the immortalization or stable genetic modification of an existing culture or line).
addition of molecular label
The addition of phycoerytherin label to an anti-CD8 antibody, to label all antibodies. The addition of anti-CD8-PE to a population of cells, to label the subpopulation cells that are CD8+.
labeling
OBI developer call, 3-12-12
a material processing technique intended to add a molecular label to some input material entity, to allow detection of the molecular target of this label in a detection of molecular label assay
PERSON:Matthew Brush
molecular cloning
pa_branch (Alan, Randi, Kevin, Jay, Bjoern)
recombinant vector cloning
a planned process with the objective to insert genetic material into a cloning vector for future replication of the inserted material
OBI branch derived
PlanAndPlannedProcess Branch
nucleic acid extraction
a material separation to recover the nucleic acid fraction of an input material
OBI branch derived
requested by Helen Parkinson for MO. Could be defined class
Phenol / chlorophorm extraction disolvation of protein content folllowed by ethanol precipitation of the nucleic acid fraction over night in the fridge followed by centrifugation to obtain a nucleic acid pellet.
a phage display library is a collection of materials in which a mixture of genes or gene fragments is expressed and can be individually selected and amplified.
PMID: 15905471.Nucleic Acids Res. 2005 May 19;33(9):e81.Oligonucleotide-assisted cleavage and ligation: a novel directional DNA cloning technology to capture cDNAs. Application in the construction of a human immune antibody phage-display library. [Phage display library encoding fragments of human antibodies. m-rna library encoding for 9-mer peptides]
phage display library
PERSON: Bjoern Peters
PERSON: Philippe Rocca-Serra
WEB: http://www.immuneepitope.org/home.do
display library
target of material addition
IEDB
A material entity into which another is being added in a material combinatino process
10/26/09: This defined class is used as a &apos;macro&apos; to reduce the size of the IEDB export.
A cell culture into which a mixture of peptides is being added.
protein
antithrombin III is a protein
An amino acid chain that is produced de novo by ribosome-mediated translation of a genetically-encoded mRNA.
molecular label
molecular tracer
a molecular reagent intended to associate with some molecular target to serve as a proxy for the presence, abundance, or location of this target in a detection of molecular label assay
OBI developer call, 3-12-12
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
x-axis is a cartesian coordinate axis which is orthogonal to the y-axis and the z-axis
L&apos;axe desx estl&apos;axe des coordonnees cartésiennes qui est orthogonal à l&apos;axe des y et l&apos;axes des z.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
y-axis is a cartesian coordinate axis which is orthogonal to the x-axis and the z-axis
Orlaith Burke
L&apos;axe desy estl&apos;axe des coordonnees cartésiennes qui est orthogonal à l&apos;axe des x et l&apos;axes des z.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
A Cartesian coordinate system is a coordinate system that specifies each point uniquely in a plane by a pair of numerical coordinates, which are the signed distances from the point to two fixed perpendicular directed lines, measured in the same unit of length.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartesian_coordinate_system
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Un système de coordonnées cartésiennes est un système de coordonnées qui spécifie chaque point de manière unique dans un plan par une paire de coordonnées numériques, qui sont les distances aupoint d&apos;originemesurées dans la même unité de longueur le long des axes x, y et z.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syst%C3%A8me_de_coordonn%C3%A9es
En géométrie, un système de coordonnées est un système qui utilise un ou plusieurs nombres, ou des coordonnées, pour déterminer de manière unique la position d&apos;un point ou d&apos;un autre élément géométrique sur un repère tel que l&apos;espace euclidien.
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coordinate_system
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
In geometry, a coordinate system is a system which uses one or more numbers, or coordinates, to uniquely determine the position of a point or other geometric element on a manifold such as Euclidean space.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran


Un axe catésien est un des trois axes dans un système de coordonnées cartésien défini comme un référentiel à trois dimensions. Chaque axe est orthogonal aux deux autres.
a cartesian axis is one of 3 the axis in a cartesian coordinate system defining a referential in 3 dimensions. each of the axis is orthogonal to the other 2
rectangular coordinate axis
Orlaith Burke
z-axis is a cartesian coordinate axis which is orthogonal to the x-axis and the y-axis
STATO
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
L&apos;axe desz estl&apos;axe des coordonnees cartésiennes qui est orthogonal à l&apos;axe des x et l&apos;axes des y.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Un système de coordonnées cartésiennes bidimensionnelles est un système de coordonnées cartésiennes qui définit 2 axes orthogonaux et qui peut être utilisé pour décrire une région spatiale bidimensionnelle
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
 a 2 dimensional cartesian coordinate system is a cartesian coordinate system which defines 2 orthogonal one dimensional axes and which may be used to describe a 2 dimensional spatial region
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
A cartesian spatial coordinate datum chosen as a fixed point of reference in a three dimensional spatial region.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Une donnée de coordonnées spatiales cartésiennes choisie comme point de référence fixe dans une région spatiale tridimensionnelle.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une donnée de coordonnées spatiales cartésiennes choisie comme point de référence fixe dans une région spatiale bidimensionnelle.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
A cartesian spatial coordinate datum chosen as a fixed point of reference in a two dimensional spatial region.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Un système de coordonnées cartésienne unidimensionnelle est un système de coordonnées cartésiennes qui définit une dimension unique.
 a three dimensional cartesian coordinate system is a cartesian coordinate system which defines 3 orthogonal one dimensional axis and which may be used to describe a 3 dimensional spatial region
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
The studentized range (q) distribution is a probability distribution used by the Tukey Honestl

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
La distribution de l&apos;étendue studentisée (q) est une distribution de probabilités utilisée par le Tukey Honestly Significant Difference test [NDT éq

A Dictionary of Statistics (2 rev e

q distribution
http://www.stat.duke.edu/courses/Spring98/sta110c/qtable.html
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
 a three dimensional cartesian coordinate system is a cartesian coordinate system which defines 3 orthogonal one dimensional axes and which may be used to describe a 3 dimensional spatial region
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Un système de coordonnées cartésiennes tridimensionnelles est un système de coordonnées cartésiennes qui définit 3 axes unidimensionnels orthogonaux et qui peut être utilisé pour décrire une région spatiale à 3 dimensions &quot;
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Une donnée de coordonnées spatiales cartésiennes choisie comme un point de référence fixe dans une région spatiale unidimensionnelle.
A cartesian spatial coordinate datum chosen as a fixed point of reference in a one dimensional spatial region.
Jean-Marc Meunier
placeholder, more work needed
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
A cartesian spatial coordinate datum chosen as a fixed point of reference in a spatial region.
l&apos;origine de coordonnées spatiales cartésiennes choisie est une point de référence fixe dans une région spatiale.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
C&apos;est la mesure de la variation ou dispersion statistiques d

STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
measure of variation or statistical dispersion is a data item which describes how much a theoritical distribution or dataset is spread.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Mesure de dispersion
Adaptée de http://grasland.script.univ-paris-diderot.fr/STAT98/stat98_4/stat98_4.htm
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
a measure of central tendency is a data item which attempts to describe a set of data by identifying the value of its centre.
Une mesure de tendance centrale est un élément de données qui tente de décrire un ensemble de données en identifiant la valeur de son centre.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
La statistique du Chi-carré est une statistique calculée à partir des observations et utilisée pour produire une valeur p dans le test statistique par rapport à une distribution Chi-carré.
STATO
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Chi-squared statistic is a statistic computed from observations and used to produce a p-value in statistical test when compared to a Chi-Squared distribution.
Jean-Marc Meunier
En statistique, le mode ou valeur dominante désigne la valeur la plus représentée d&apos;une variable quelconque dans une population d&apos;objets, de personnes, de choses. Une répartition peut être unimodale ou plurimodale (bimodale, trimodale…) voire sans aucun mode (distribution uniforme), si deux ou plusieurs valeurs de la variable considérée émergent également.
Orlaith Burke
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mode_(statistiques)
Philippe Rocca-Serra
The mode is a data item which corresponds to the most frequently occurring number in a set of numbers.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran

Je ne suis pas d&apos;accord sur la position du mode. Ce n&apos;est pas une sorte de médiane.ni une tendance central dans la mesure où le mode peut ne pas être au centre d&apos;une distribution.
http://www.sagepub.com/upm-data/47775_ch_3.pdf
STATO
Jeean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Un paramètre de modèle est une donnée qui fait partie d&apos;un modèle et qui est destiné à caractériser une population théorisée ou inconnue. Un paramètre de modèle peut être estimé en considérant les propriétés des échantillons présumés tirés de la population théorique.
Orlaith Burke
a model parameter is a data item which is part of a model and which is meant to characterize an theoritecal or unknown population. a model parameter may be estimated by considering the properties of samples presumably taken from the theoritecal population
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://www.sagepub.com/upm-data/47775_ch_3.pdf
Outliers sont des scores déviants qui ont été légitimement recueillis et ne sont pas dues à des pannes d&apos;équipement.
Outliers are deviant scores that have been legitimately gathered and are not due to equipment failures.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
SEM
Orlaith Burke
Erreur type de la moyenne (standard error of the mean) semble être confondue avec l&apos;erreur standard: voir la différence entr

Jean-Marc Meunier
L&apos;erreur-type de la moyenne (terme utilisé pour la première fois par Yule, 1897) est l&apos;écart-type théorique de toutes les moyennes d&apos;échantillons de taille n extraites à partir d&apos;une population et dépend de la variance de la population (sigma) et de la taille d&apos;échantillon (n).
The standard error of the mean (SEM) is data item denoting the standard deviation of the sample-mean&apos;s

http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/e/erreur-moyenne.html
adapted from wikipedia (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_error)
http://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/50623/r-calculating-mean-and-standard-error-of-mean-for-factors-with-lm-vs-direct
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
possibly submit to &apos;Population and Community Ontology&apos;
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Ensemble de sujets résultant d&apos;un processus d&apos;appariement dans lequel les sujets sont assignés à un ensemble sur la base de règles d&apos;appariement.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a set of 2 subjects which result from a pairing process which assigns subject to a set based on a pairing rule/criteria
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Une statistique est une donnée de mesure utilisée pour décrire un ensemble de données ou une variable. Il est généré par un calcul sur l&apos;ensemble des données observées.
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistic).

Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Les sous-classes de &quot;statistique&quot; me semblent très limitatives. Pourquoi les indices descriptifs n&apos;y sont pas, pourquoi n&apos;y a-t-ilpas les coefficients et les corrélations ?
a statistic is a measurement datum to describe a dataset or a variable. It is generated by a calculation on set of observed data.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/a/darling.html
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anderson_Darling_test
La procédure Anderson-Darling (NIST, 2005 ; Press, et al, 1992) est un test général permettant de comparer l&apos;ajustement d&apos;une fonction de répartition observée cumulée à une fonction de répartition théorique cumulée. Ce test est applicable à un ensemble de données complet (sans observations censurées) et constitue une alternative au test de Kolmogorov-Smirnov pour deux échantillons. Si le test de Kolmogorov-Smirnov est assez sensible à la médiane (et donc bien adapté pour détecter des écarts entre les distributions cumulées), le test d&apos;Anderson-Darling est plus sensible sur toute l&apos;étendue de la distribution et a donc plus de chances de détecter des différences dans la répartition des distributions cumulées. Ainsi, le test d&apos;Anderson-Darling est préférable pour savoir si les données simulées modélisent bien les données obse

Orlaith Burke
The Anderson–Darling test is a statistical test of whether a given sample of data is drawn from a given probability distribution.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Anova à un facteur est une analyse de variance où les différents groupes comparés sont associés à une seule variable indépendante. L&apos;hypothèse nulle est une absence de différence entre les moyens calculés pour chacun des groupes. Le test suppose la normalité et l&apos;homogénéité des variances.
one-way anova is an analysis of variance where the different groups being compared are associated with the factor levels of only one independent variable. The null hypothesis is an absence of difference between the means calculated for each of the groups. The test assumes normality and equivariance of the data.
Analyse de variance à un facteur
Orlaith Burke
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
one factor ANOVA
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
two-way anova is an analysis of variance where the different groups being compared are associated the factor levels of exatly 2 independent variables. The null hypothesis is an absence of difference between the means calculated for each of the groups. The test assumes normality and equivariance of the data.
Jean-Marc Meunier
ANOVA à deux facteurs est une analyse de variance où les différents groupes comparés sont associés deux variables indépendantes seulement. L&apos;hypothèse nulle est une absence de différence entre les moyenness calculées pour chacun des groupes. Le test suppose la normalité et l&apos;homogénéité des variances.
Orlaith Burke
STATO
two factor ANOVA
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Analyse de variance à deux facteurs
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Multi-way anova is an analysis of variance where the difference groups being compared are associated to the factor levels of more than 2 independent variables. The null hypothesis is an absence of difference between the means calculated for each of the groups. The test assumes normality and equivariance of the data.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
l&apos;Anova multiple est une analyse de variance où les groupes de comparés sont associés à plus de 2 variables indépendantes. L&apos;hypothèse nulle est une absence de différence entre les moyennes calculées pour chacun des groupes. Le test suppose la normalité et l&apos;équivalité des données.
http://reference.wolfram.com/mathematica/ref/ZTest.html
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Z-test is a statistical test which evaluate the null hypothesis that the means of 2 populations are equal and returns a p-value.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Le test Z est un test statistique qui évalue l&apos;hypothèse nulle selon laquelle les moyennes de 2 populations sont égales et renvoie une valeur p.
PRS,AGB adapted from wikipedia and wolfram alpha
Orlaith Burke
Erreur de type 1
a false positive rate is a data item which accounts for the proportion of incorrect reject

Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Un taux de faux positif est une donnée qui rend compte de la proportion de rejet incorrect d&apos;une véritable hypothèse nulle.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
STATO
Hypothèse d&apos;égalité des variances
equality of variance hypothesis
L&apos;hypothèse d&apos;homoscédasticité est une hypothèse nulle postullant que toutes les variancesconsidérées sont homogènes.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
homoskedasticity is a null hypothesis stating that all variances under consideration are homogenous
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Devrait être sous la classe hypothèse nulle
Orlaith Burke
http://www.n

Philippe Rocca-Serra
chromosome coordinate system is a genomic coordinate which uses chromosome of a particular assembly build process to define start and end positions. This coordinate system is unstable and will change with each new genome sequence assembly build. 
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
Une hypothèse nulle selon laquelle il n&apos;y a pas de lien entre deux variables catégorielles.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Devrait être une sous classe d&apos;hypothèse nulle
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a null hypothesis which states that no linkage exists between 2 categorical variables
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/NullHypothesis.html
En statistiques et en économétrie, l&apos;hypothèse nulle est une hypothèse postulant l&apos;égalité entre des paramètres statistiques (généralement, la moyenne ou la variance) de deux échantillons dont elle fait l’hypothèse qu&apos;ils sont pris sur des populations équivalentes. Elle est toujours testée contre une hypothèse alternative qui postule soit la différence des données (test bilatéral dans ce cas), soit une inégalité (plus petit que ou plus grand que) entre les données (test unilatéral).
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypoth%C3%A8se_nulle
A null hypothesis is a statistical hypothesis that is tested for possible rejection under the assumption that it is true (usually that observations are the result of chance). The concept 

STATO
L&apos;hypothèse de la qualité de l&apos;ajustement est une hypothèse nulle stipulant que la distribution calculée à partir de la échantillon de lapopulation correspond à une distribution théorique ou qu&apos;un ensemble de données peut être correctement expliqué par un modèle.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
goodness of fit hypothesis is a null hypothesis stating that the distribution computed from the sample population fits a theoretical distribution or that a dataset can be correctly explained by a model
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
the Student&apos;s t distribution is a continuous probability distribution whicharises when estimating the mean of a normally distributed population in situations where the sample size is small and population standard deviation is unknown.
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Student&apos;s_t-distribution)
La distribution t de Student est une distribution de probabilité continue qui est utilisée lors de l&apos;estimation de la moyenne d&apos;une population normalement distribuée dans les situations où la taille de l&apos;échantillon est faible et l&apos;écart-type de la population est inconnu.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
hypergeometric distribution is a probability distribution that describes the probability ofk successes in n draws from a finite population of sizeN containingK successes without replacement
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Cette loi de probabilité discrète au nom intimidant est très proche de la loi binomiale. Elle décrit comme elle une suite d’épreuves dont le résultat aléatoire est binaire (de type succès vs échec). La seule différence est qu’une même pièce, ou un même individu, ne peut apparaître deux fois. Il s’agit donc d’un tirage exhaustif, c

http://www.jybaudot.fr/Probas/hypergeometrique.html
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypergeometric_distribution
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
It is a null hypothesis stating that there are no differences observed between group of subjects.
C&apos;est une hypothèse nulle qui postule qu&apos;il n&apos;y apas de différence entre les groupes de sujets.
STATO
Devrait être une sous classe d&apos;hypothèse nulle
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Devrait être une sous classe d&apos;une hypothèse nulle
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
is a null hypothesis stating that there are no difference observed across a series of measurements made one same subject.
C&apos;est une hypothèse nulle postulant qu&apos;il n&apos;y a pas de différence observée au cours d&apos;une série de mesures réalisées pour un même individu.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://left.subtree.org/2012/04/13/counting-the-number-of-reads-in-a-bam-file/
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
AGB-PRS, STATO
sequence read count is a data item determining how many sequence reads generated by a DNA sequencing assay for a given stretch of DNA can counted


Jean-Marc Meunier
a continuous probability distribution is a probability distribution which is defined by a probability density function
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Une distribution de probabilités continue est une distribution de probabilités définie par une fonction de densité de probabilités.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Skewness is a data item indicating of the degree of asymmetry of adistribution.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Skewness.html
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
En théorie des probabilités et statistique, le coefficient de dissymétrie (skewness en anglais) correspond à une mesure de l’asymétrie de la distribution d’u

Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asym%C3%A9trie_(statistiques)
Orlaith Burke
The number degree of freedom is a count evaluating the number of values in a calculation that can vary. In statistics, the number of degrees of freedom ν is equal to N-1 in the case of the direct measurement of a quantity estimated by the arithmetic mean of N independent observations.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://www.optique-ingenieur.org/en/courses/OPI

http://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/16921/how-to-understand-degrees-of-freedom
the rank of the quadratic form (mathematical definition)
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
L&apos;approximation de la statistique du Chi² pour les petits tableaux 2 x 2 peut être améliorée en réduisant de 0,5 la valeur absolue des différences entre les effectifs théoriques et les effectifs observés avant de l&apos;élever au carré (correction de Yates). Cette correction, qui rend l&apos;estimation plus conservatrice est souvent appliquée lorsque la table ne contient que peu d&apos;effectifs observés, et que les effectifs théoriques deviennent inférieurs à 10 (pour une présentation plus approfondie de cette correction, voir Conover, 1974; Everitt, 1977 ; Hays, 1988; Kendall &amp; Stuart, 1979 et Mantel, 1974).
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/c/chi-corrige.html
Yate&apos;s corrected Chi-Squared test is a statistical test which is used to test the association/linkage/independence of 2 dichotomous variables while introducing a correction for using the continous Chi-squ

STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yates&apos;s_correction_for_continuity) polled in June 2013
duplicate with OBI_0200176. so either MIREOT and add metadata and axioms or move from OBI
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_exact_de_Fisher
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/FishersExactTest.html
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Fisher&apos;s exact test is a statistical test used to determine if there are nonrandom associations between two categorical variables.
Orlaith Burke
Le Test exact de Fisher est un test statistique utilisé pour l&apos;analyse des tables de contingence. Ce test est utilisé en général avec des faibles effectifs mais il est valide pour toutes les tailles d&apos;échantillon. Il doit son nom à son inventeur Ronald Fisher. C&apos;est un test qualifié d&apos;exact car les probabilités peuvent être calculées exactement plutôt qu&apos;en s&apos;appuyant sur une approximation qui ne devient correcte qu&apos;asymptotiquement comme pour le test du chi ^ utilisé 

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://lemakistatheux.wordpress.com/2013/08/28/le-test-du-chi2-de-mantel-haenszel/
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cochran–Mantel–Haenszel_statistics) and from the Handbook of Biological Statistics (http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statcmh.html)
Cochran-Mantel-Haenzel test for repeated tests of independence is a statitiscal test which allows the comparison of two groups on a dichotomous/categorical response. It is used when the effect of the explanatory variable on the response variable is influenced by covariates that can be controlled. It is often used in observational studies where random assignment of subjects to different treatments cannot be controlled, 

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Publié en 1959 par Nathan Mantel, William Haenszel et basé sur les travaux de William Gemmel Cochran de 1954, le test du \chi^2 de Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel est une approche non paramétrique permettant de tester si « l’odds ration commun » associé à une succession de tableaux croisés dynamiques issue de variables qualitatives deux à deux appariées (X ^{t_1}, X ^{t_2}), (X ^{t_2}, X ^{t_3}), (X ^{t_3}, X ^{t_4}), \cdots , (X ^{t_{n - 2}}, X ^{t_{n - 1}}), (X ^{t_{n - 1}}, X ^{t_n}) à 2 modalités s’éloigne de 1 ou non. On rappel qu’une odds ratio égal à 1 implique une pente inexistante
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Une courbe de raréfaction est un graphique utilisé pour estimer la richesse en espèces dans les études écologiques.
a rarefaction curve is a graph used for estimating species richness in ecology studies
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
STATO
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_de_Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney
The Mann-Whitney U-test is a null hypothesis statistical testing procedure which allows two groups (or conditions or treatments) to be compared without making the assumption that va

Le test de Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney (ou test U de Mann-Whitney ou encore test de la somme des rangs de Wilcoxon) est un test statistique non paramétrique qui permet de tester l&apos;hypothèse selon laquelle la distribution des données est la même dans deux groupes. Il a été proposé par Frank Wilcoxon en 19451 et par Henry Mann et 

adapted from http://udel.edu/~

U test
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Wilcoxon rank-sum test
rank-sum test for the comparison of two samples
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
S-W test
Orlaith Burke
Shapiro-Wilk test is a goodness of fit test which evaluates the null hypothesis that the sample is drawn from a population following a normal distribution
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le test de Shapiro-Wilk (W) est utilisé pour tester la normalité. Si la statistique W est significative, il faut alors rejeter l&apos;hypothèse selon laquelle la distribution correspondante est normale. Le test W de Shapiro-Wilk est le test de normalité le plus utilisé parce que c&apos;est un test puissant par rapport à de nombreux tests alternatifs (Shapiro, Wilk, &amp; Chen, 1968). STATISTICA développe une extension du test décrite par Royston (1982), qui permet de l&apos;appliquer à de grands échantillons (avec jusqu&apos;à 2,000 observations). Voir également les rubriques Test de Kolmogorov-Smirnov et Test de Lilliefors.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shapiro–Wilk_test)
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/t/test-shapiro-wilk.html
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://lemakistatheux.wordpress.com/2013/08/04/le-test-de-levene/
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Publié en 1960 suite aux travaux d’Howard Levene, letest de Levene est une approche paramétrique permettant de tester si les sous-échantillons X|Y = g_1, ... , X|Y = g_K, de X continue et restreint aux K \geq 2 groupes d’une variable Y q

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levene_test
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Levene&apos;s test is a null hypothesis statistical test which evaluates the null hypothesis of equality of variance in several populations.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartlett_test
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_de_Bartlett
Bartlett&apos;s test (see Snedecor and Cochran, 1989) is used to test if k samples are from populations with equal variances. Equal variances across samples is called homoscedasticity or homogeneity of variances. Some statistical tests, for example the analysis of variance, assume that variances are equal across groups or samples. The Bartlett test can be 

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Le test de Bartlett du nom du statisticien anglais Maurice Stevenson Bartlett (18 juin 1910 – 8 janvier 2002) est utilisé en statistique pour évaluer si k échantillons indépendants sont issus de populations de même variance (condition dite d&apos;homoscédasticité). C&

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
adapted from Wikipedia and Brown, M. B., and A. B. Forsythe. 1974a. The small sample behavior of some statistics which test the equality of several means. Technometrics, 16, 129-132.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
the Brown Forsythe test is a statistical test which evaluates if the variance of different groups are equal. It relies on computing the median rather than the mean, as used in the Levene&

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Le test Brown Forsythe est un test statistique qui évalue si la variance des différents groupes est égale. Il s&apos;appuie sur le calcul de la médiane plutôt que de la moyenne, tel qu&apos;utilisé dans le test de Levene pour l&apos;homoscédasticité.Ce test peut être utilisé, par exemple, pour garantir que les conditions d&apos;application de l&apos;ANOVA sont respectées.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier


La définition anglaise évoque le chi deux d&apos;ajustement, est-ce normale ?
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Pearson&apos;s Chi-Squared test is a statistical null hypothesis test which is used to either evaluate goodness of fit of dataset to a Chi-Squared distribution or used to test independenceof 2 categorical variables (ie absence of association between those variables).
Le test chi carré d&apos;indépendance est un test statistique d&apos;hypothèse nulle qui sert à évaluer l&apos;indépendance de 2 variables catégoriques (c&apos;est-à-dire absence d&apos;association entre ces variables).
Chi2 test for independence
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
K-S test


http://www.itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/eda/section3/eda35g.htm
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
En statistiques, le test de Kolmogorov-Smirnov est un test d&apos;hypothèse utilisé pour déterminer si un échantillon suit bien une loi donnée connue par sa fonction de répartition continue, ou bien si deux échantillons suivent la même loi.
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_de_Kolmogorov-Smirnov
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kolmogorov–Smirnov_test)
Kolmogorov-Smirnov test is a goodness of fit test which evaluates the null hypothesis that a sample is drawn from a population that follows a specific continuous probability distribution.
Jean-Marc Meunier
AGB,PRS
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
L&apos;estimation de la valeur de l&apos;effet est un élément de données sur la direction et la force des conséquences d&apos;un agent causal exploré par des méthodes statistiques. Ces méthodes produisent des estimations de la valeur de l&apos;effet, par exemple dans un intervalle de confiance.
effect size estimate is a data item about the direction and strength of the consequences of a causative agent as explored by statistical methods. Those methods produce estimates of the effect size, e.g. confidence interval
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2689604/
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Test de Fisher
Le test de Fisher, ou test F, est un test d&apos;hypothèse statistique qui permet de tester l&apos;égalité de deux variances en faisant le rapport des deux variances et en vérifiant que ce rapport ne dépasse pas une certaine valeur théorique que l&apos;on cherche dans la table de Fisher (ou table de Snedecor).
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_de_Fisher
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
an F-test is a statistical test which evaluates that the computed test statistics follows an F-distribution under the null hypothesis. The F-test is sensitive to departure from normality. F-test arise when decomposing the variability in a data set in terms of sum of squares.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
La taille de l&apos;échantillon statistique est le nombre d&apos;individus statistiques
Orlaith Burke
AGB-PRS
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
statistical sample size is a count evaluating the number of individual experimental units
Genome wide association study is a kind of study whose objective is to detect association between genetic markers (SNP or otherwise) accross the genome and a trait which may be a disease or another phenotype (e.g. trait of agronomic relevance in animal or plant studies). Genome wide association study compare the allele frequencies in 2 populations, one free of the trait used as control, the other one showing the trait use as &apos;case&apos;. GWAS studies implement case-control design
AGB, PRS
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Il s’agit d’un test de rangs sur échantillons APPARIÉS, c’est-à-dire qu’il peut être utilisé chaque fois que des répondants à une enquête donnent leur avis sur une échelle (du type : note de 1 à 5), avant d’être réinterrogés après un évènement. Celui-ci peut concerner les ressources humaines (évaluation d’une formation, évaluation d’un ressenti par un audit social) mais surtout le marketing (évaluation auprès d’un panel d’une nouvelle image de marque, par exemple). Non paramétrique, il s&apos;accommode de distributions asymétriques ou de variances différentes entre la première enquête et la seconde.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
The Wilcoxon signed rank test is a statistical test which tests the null hypothesis that the median difference between pairs of observations is zero. This is the non-parametric analogue to the paired t-test, and should be used if the distribution of differences between pairs m

Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statsignedrank.html
http://www.jybaudot.fr/Inferentielle/wilcoxon.html
H test
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Le test de Kruskal-Wallis est une alternative non-paramétrique à l&apos;ANOVA d&apos;ordre Un (inter-groupes). Il est utilisé pour comparer au moins trois échantillons, et tester l&apos;hypothèse nulle suivant laquelle les différents échantillons à comparer sont issus de la même distribution ou de distributions de même médiane. Ainsi, l&apos;interprétation du test de Kruskal-Wallis est très similaire à une ANOVA paramétrique d&apos;ordre Un, sauf qu&apos;il est basé sur les rangs au lieu des moyennes. Pour plus de détails, voir Siegel &amp; Castellan, 1988. Voir aussi, les Tests Non-Paramétriques.
rank-sum test for the comparison of multiple (more than 2) samples
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
The Kruskal–Wallis test is a null hypothesis statistical testing objective whichallows multiple (n&gt;=2) groups (or conditions or treatments) to be compared, without making the assumption that values are normally distributed. The Kruskal–Wallis test is the non-parametric equivalent o

http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statkruskalwallis.html
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Test pour des échantillons appariés. Le test-t pour des échantillons appariés peut être utilisé pour analyser les plans dans lesquels la dispersion intra-groupe (contribuant normalement à l&apos;erreur de mesure) peut être facilement identifiée et éliminée de l&apos;analyse. Plus précisément, si les deux groupes de mesures à comparer sont basés sur le même échantillon d&apos;observations (par exemple, des sujets) testé deux fois (par exemple, avant et après un traitement), alors une part considérable de la dispersion intra-groupe dans les deux groupes de résultats peut être attribuée aux différences individuelles initiales entre les observations et ainsi expliquée (c&apos;est-à-dire, retranchée de l&apos;erreur). Ceci permet d&apos;augmenter la sensibilité du plan.
http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statpaired.html
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statsignedrank.html
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/t/test-t.html
paired t-test is a statistical test which is specifically designed to analysis differences between paired observations in the case of studies realizing repeated measures design with only 2 repeated measurements per subject (before and after treatment for example)
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran


stratification is a planned process which executes a stratification rule using as input a population and assign it member to mutually exclusive subpopulation based on the values defined by the stratification rule
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Hotelling&apos;s T2 test is a statistical test which is a generalization of Student&apos;s T-test to a assess if the means of a set of variables remains unchanged when studying 2 populations. It is a type of multivariate analysis
http://arxiv.org/pdf/1007.1094.pdf
STATO
Le test T2 d&apos;Hotelling est un test statistique qui est une généralisation du test T de Sutudent pour évaluer si les moyennes d&apos;un ensemble de variables restent inchangées lors de l&apos;étude de 2 populations. C&apos;est un type d&apos;analyse multivariée
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
SMD
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
standardized mean difference is data item computed by forming the difference between two means, divided by an estimate of the w

adapted from http://htaglossary.net/sta

adapted from &quot;Effect size, confidence interval and statistical significance: a practical guide for biolo

La différence de moyenne standardisée est l&apos;élément de données calculé en faisant la différence entre deux moyennes, divisé par une estimation de l&apos;écart-type dans le groupe.Il est utilisé pour fournir une estimation de la taille de l&apos;effet entre deux traitements lorsque le prédicteur (variable indépendante) est catégorique et la variable de réponse (dépendante) est continue.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Score centré réduit
Un z-score (également connu sous le nom de valeur de z, score standard ou score normal) est une mesure de la divergence d&apos;un résultat expérimental individuel et du résultat le plus probable, la moyennre. Z est exprimé en nombre d&apos;écarts types par rapport à la valeur moyenne.
https://controls.engin.umich.edu/wiki/index.php/Basic_statistics:_mean,_median,_average,_standard_deviation,_z-scores,_and_p-value#Z-Scores
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
A z-score (also known as z-value, standard score, or normal score) is a measure of the divergence of an individual experimental result from the most probable result, the mean. Z is expressed in terms of the number of standard deviations from the mean value.
Un modèle statistique est une description mathématique approximative du mécanisme qui a généré les observations, que l&apos;on suppose être un processus stochastique et non un processus déterministe. Il s’exprime généralement à l’aide d’une famille de distributions (ensemble de distributions) et d’hypothèses sur les variables aléatoires X1, . . ., Xn. Chaque membre de la famille est une approximation possible de F : l’inférence consiste donc à déterminer le membre qui s’acco

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran


a statistical model is an information content entity which is a formalization of relationships between variables in the form of mathematical equations. A statistical model describes how one or more random variables are related to one or more other variables. The model is statistical as the variables are not deterministically but stochastically related.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le_statistique
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/R%C3%A9gression_lin%C3%A9aire
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_regression) polled in June 2013
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
linear regression model is a model which attempts to explain data distribution associated with response/dependent variable in terms of values assumed by the independent variable uses a linear function or linear combination of the regression parameters and the pre

En statistiques, en économétrie et en apprentissage automatique, un modèle de régression linéaire est un modèle de régression qui cherche à établir une relation linéaire entre une variable, dite expliquée, et une ou plusieurs

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a sequence read is a DNA sequence data which is generated by a DNA sequencer
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
σ2
En statistique et en théorie des probabilités, la variance est une mesure servant à caractériser la dispersion d&apos;un échantil

Philippe Rocca-Serra
variance is a data item about a random variable or probability distribution. it is equivalent to the square of the standard deviation.It is one of several descriptors of a probability distribution, describing how far the numbers lie from the mean (expected value).The variance is the second moment of a distribution.
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variance_(statistiques_et_probabilit%C3%A9s)
Alejandra Gonzalez-Belran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
From &quot;The strenght of statistical evi

Orlaith Burke
the process of using statistical analysis for interpreting and communicating &quot;what the data say&quot;.
STATO
ranking is a data transformation which turns a non-ordinal variable into a Ordinal variable by sorting the values of the input variable and replacing their value by their position in the sorting result
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
le classement est une transformation de données qui transforme une variable non ordinale en une variable ordinale en triant les valeurs de la variable d&apos;entrée et en remplaçant leur valeur par leur position dans le résultat de tri.
Orlaith Burke
model parameter estimation is a data transformation that finds parameter values (the model parameter estimates) most compatible with the data as judged by the model.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
textual definition modified following c


L&apos;estimation des paramètres du modèle est une transformation de données qui trouve les valeurs des paramètres (les estimations des paramètres du modèle) les plus compatibles avec les données jugées par le modèle.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
the objective of a data transformation to evaluate a null hypothesis of absence of linkage between variables.
C&apos;est un objectif d&apos;une transformation de données pour évaluer une hypothèse nulle d&apos;absence de liaison entre les variables&quot;.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO adapted from wikipedia (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedigree_chart)
Un arbre de généalogie est un graphique qui reproduit les relations parents-enfants.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a pedigree chart is a graph which plots parent child relations
Philippe Rocca-Serra
a stratification rule/criteria is a criteria used to determine population strata so that a stratification process implementing the rule can result in any member of the total population being assigned to one and only one stratum
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke


STATO
Une règle / critère de stratification est un critère utilisé pour déterminer les strates de population de sorte qu&apos;un processus de stratification mettant en œuvre la règle peut entraîner l&apos;attribution d&apos;un membre de la population totale à une seule et à une strate.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
volcano plot is a kind of scatter plot which graphs the negative log of the p-value (significance) on the y-axis versus log2 of fold-change betw

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volcano_plot_(statistics)
Le diagramme en volcan est une sorte de diagramme de dispersion qui représente le log négatif de la valeur p (importance) sur l&apos;axe des y versus log2 de repliement entre 2 conditions sur l&apos;axe des abscisses.C&apos;est une méthode populaire pour visualiser l&apos;apparition différentielle de variables entre 2 conditions.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le test de Breslow-Day est un test statistique qui évalue si les odds ratios sont homogènes dans N tables de contingence 2x2, par exemple plusieurs tables de contingence 2x2 associées à différentes couches d&apos;une population stratifiée lors de l&apos;évaluation de la relation entre l&apos;exposition et le résultat ou associée aux différents Échantillons provenant de plusieurs centres dans une étude multicentrique dans le contexte des essais cliniques.
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2288/11/58#B9
Philippe Rocca-Serra
the Breslow-Day test is a statistical test which evaluates if the odds ratios are homogenous across N 2x2 contingency tables, for instance several 2x2 contingency tables associated with different strata of a stratified population when evaluating the relationship between exposure and outcome or associated with the different samples coming from several centres in a multicentric study in clinical trial context.
Orlaith Burke




Jean-Marc Meunier
https://lemakistatheux.wordpress.com/2013/08/13/le-t-carre-dhotelling/
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Hotelling T squared distribution is a probability distribution used in multivariate hypothesis testing, which is a univariate distribution proportional to the F-distribution and arises importantly as the distribution of a set of statistics which are natural generalizations of the statistics underlying

Publié en 1931 suite aux travaux d’Harold Hotelling, le T ^2 de Hotelling est une approche paramétrique permettant de tester si plusieurs variables continues distinctes \mathbf{X} = (X ^1, \cdots, X ^P) sont liées à une variable qualitative binaire Y lorsqu’elles sont considérées avec leurs différen

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
specificity is a measurement datum qualifying a binary classification test and is computed by substracting the false positive rate to the integral numeral 1
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sensibilit%C3%A9_et_sp%C3%A9cificit%C3%A9
specificity
Jean-Marc Meunier
La spécificitémesure la capacité d&apos;un test à donner un résultat négatif lorsque l&apos;hypothèse n&apos;est pas vérifiée. Ainsi, la spécificité, correspond àla probabilité d&apos;obtenir un test négatif. Elle est donnée par le rappport VN/(VN+FP) où VN est le nombre de vrais négatifs et FP, le nombre de faux positifs de faux positifs.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Spécificité
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SSMD
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2789971/
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2789971/
La différence de moyenne strictement normalisée (SSMD) est une différence de moyenne standardisée qui correspond au rapport entre la moyenne et l&apos;écart-type de la différence entre deux groupes. SSMD mesure directement l&apos;ampleur de la différence entre deux groupes.
strictly standardized mean difference (SSMS) is a standardized mean difference which corresponds to theratio of mean to the standard deviation of the 

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Tarone&apos;s test for homogeneity of odds ratio is a statistical test which evaluates the null hypothesis that odds ratio are homogeneous
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
STATO
Une table de contingence 2x2 est une table construite avec deux variables dichotomiques (c&apos;est-à-dire deux varaibles catégorielles ayant chacune deux modalités). C&apos;est la plus simple des tables de contingence.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a 2x2 contingency table is a contingency table build for 2 dichotomous variables (i.e. 2 categorical variables, each with only 2 possible outcomes). It is the simplest of contingency tables
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
pairing patients by age, pairing animals by body weight range
Orlaith Burke
a subject pairing is a planned process which executes a pairing rule and results in the creation of sets of 2 subjects meeting the pairing criteria
STATO
Jean-Marc Marc Meunier
Un couplage de sujet est un processus planifié qui exécute une règle d&apos;appariement et entraîne la création d&apos;ensembles de 2 sujets répondant aux critères d&apos;appariement.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Un appariement de sujets est un processus planifié qui exécute une règle d&apos;appariement et entraîne la création d&apos;ensembles de 2 sujets répondant aux critères d&apos;appariement
Philippe Rocca-Serra
a contigency table is a data item which displays the (multivariate) frequency distribution of the possible v

Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coordonn%C3%A9es_cylindriques
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contingency_table)
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Un tableau de contingence est une méthode de représentation de données issues d’un comptage permettant d&apos;estimer la dépendance entre deux caractères. Elle consiste à croiser deux caractères d&apos;une population (par exemple une classe d&apos;âge et un score) en dénombrant l&apos;effectif correspondant à la conjonction « caract

STATO
Jean-Marc Meunier
The correlation coefficient of two variables in a data sample is their covariance divided by the product of their individual standard deviations. It is a normalized measurement of how the two are linearly related.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Le coefficient de corrélation de deux variables dans un échantillon de données est leur covariance divisée par le produit de leurs écarts types individuels. C&apos;est une mesure normalisée de la façon dont les deux sont linéairement liés.
Jean-Marc Meunier
a Bayesian model selection is a data transformation which is based on Bayesian statistics to compute Bayes factor in order to evaluate which model best explains data.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Une sélection d&apos;un modèle bayésien est une transformation de donnée basée sur des statistiques bayésiennes pour calculer le facteur de Bayes dans le but d&apos;évaluer le modèle qui explique le mieux les données.


Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
STATO
a model parameter estimate is a data item which results from a model parameter estimation process and which provides a numerical value about a model parameter.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
for example , model parameter estimates could beproduced usingregression analysis(used in a model estimation process) , which attempts to express the response variable in terms of function of predictor variable and model parameters.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Alejandra Gonzalez Beltran
textual definition modified following c

Une estimation de paramètre de modèle est une donnée qui résulte d&apos;un processus d&apos;estimation de paramètre de modèle et qui fournit une valeur numérique à propos d&apos;un paramètre de modèle.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le graphique de déséquilibre de liaison est un graphique qui représente des mesures de déséquilibre de liaison par paire entre SNP en tant que carte de chaleur.
STATO, adapted fromR documentation (http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/LDheatmap/index.html)
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Linkage Disequilibrium plot is a graph which represents pairwise linkage disequilibrium measures between SNP as a heatmap
The Cochran-Armitage test is a statistical test used in categorical data analysis when the aim is to assess for the presence of an association between a dichotomous variable (variable with two categories) and a polychotomous variable

Philippe Rocca-Serra
CATT
https://lemakistatheux.wordpress.com/2013/09/15/le-test-de-tendance-de-cochran-armitage/
Publié dans une première version en 1954 par William Gemmell Cochran puis finalisé sous la forme que nous connaissons acutellement en 1955 par Peter Armitage, le test de tendance de Cochran-Armitage est une approche non paramétrique permettant de tester si deux variables qualitatives (X ^1, X ^2) à, respectivement, 2 et K 

Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cochran%E2%80%93Armitage_test_for_trend
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a minimum value is a data item which denotes the smallest value found in a dataset or resulting from a calculation.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Une valeur minimale est un élément de données qui désigne la plus petite valeur trouvée dans un ensemble de données ou résultant d&apos;un calcul.
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
maximum value is a data item which denotes the largest value found in a dataset or resulting from a calculation.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
La valeur maximale est un élément de données qui indique la plus grande valeur trouvée dans un ensemble de données ou résultant d&apos;un calcul.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Le test T2 de Hotelling est un test statistique qui est une généralisation du test T Student pour évaluer si les moyennes d&apos;un ensemble de variables restent inchangés lors de l&apos;étude de 2 populations. C&apos;est un type d&apos;analyse multivariée.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://arxiv.org/pdf/1007.1094.pdf
Hotelling&apos;s T2 test is a statistical test which is a generalization of Student&apos;s T-test to a assess if the means of a set of variables remains unchanged when studying 2 populations. It is a type of multivariate analysis
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
the Scheffe test is a data transformation which evaluates all possible contrasts and adjusting the levels significance by accounting for multiple comparison. The test is therefore conservative. Confidence intervals can be constructed for the corresponding linear regression.It was developped byAmerican statistician HenryScheffe in 1959.
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scheffé&apos;s_method)
Ce test post-hoc permet de déterminer les différences significatives entre les moyennes des groupes dans une analyse de variance. Le test de Scheffé est considéré comme l&apos;un des tests post-hoc les plus conservateurs (pour une présentation détaillée des différents tests post-hoc, voir Winer, Michels &amp; Brown (1991)). Pour plus d&apos;informations, voir le module Modèle Linéaire Général. Voir aussi les rubriques Comparaisons Post Hoc. Pour une présentation de la significativité statistique, voir la rubrique Concepts Élémentaires.
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/t/test-scheffe.html
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/f/fisher-lsd.html
the LSD testis a statistical test for multiple comparisons of treatments by means of least significant difference following an ANOVA analysis
R
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Ce test post-hoc (ou test de comparaisons multiples) peut être utilisé pour déterminer les différences significatives entre les moyennes des groupes dans une analyse de variance. Le test de Différence Significative Minimale (LSD) de Fisher est considéré comme l&apos;un des tests post-hoc les moins conservateurs (pour une présentation détaillée des différents tests post-hoc tests, voir Winer, Michels, &amp; Brown (1991)). Pour plus d&apos;informations, voir le Modèle Linéaire Général et les Comparaisons Post Hoc. Pour une présentation de la significativité statistique, voir la rubrique Concepts Élémentaires.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Test de la plus petite différence singificative
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
variable distribution is data item which denotes the spatial resolution of data point making up a variable. variable distribution may be compared to a known probability distribution using goodness of fit test or plotting a quantile-quantile plot for visual assessment of the fit.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distribution_statistique
TODO: Probably need to drop it
Philippe Rocca-Serra
En statistique, la distribution statistique, distribution empirique ou distribution des fréquences, est un tableau qui associe des classes de valeurs obtenues lors d&apos;une expérience à leurs fréquences d&apos;apparition. Ce tableau de valeurs est modélisé en théorie des probabilités par une loi de probabilité.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
the first quartile is a quartile which splits the lower 25 % of the data
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Le 1er quartile est la donnée de la série qui sépare les 25 % inférieurs des données
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Le 3e quartile est la donnée de la série qui sépare les 25 % supérieurs des données.
Orlaith Burke
the first quartile is a quartile which splits the 75 % of the data
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
homogeneity testing objective is the objective of a data transformation to test a null hypothesis that two or more sub-groups of a population share the same distribution of

STATO
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
L&apos;objectif d&apos;homogénéité est l&apos;objectif de transformation de données pour tester une hypothèse nulle selon laquelle deux ou plusieurs sous-groupes de la population partagent la même répartition d&apos;un

Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-patched/library/stats/html/confint.html
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
confidence interval calculation is a data transformation which determines a confidence interval for a given statistical parameter
Le calcul de l&apos;intervalle de confiance est une transformation de données qui détermine un intervalle de confiance pour un paramètre statistique donné
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
t-statistique est une statistique calculée à partir d&apos;observations et utilisées pour produire une p-valeur test statistique par rapport à une distribution t de Student.
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
t-statistic is a statistic computed from observations and used to produce a p-value in statistical test when compared to a Student&apos;s t distribution.
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Kurtosis is a data item which denotes the degree of peakedness of a distribution. It is defined as a normalized form of the fourth central moment of a distribution. 
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurtosis
Applatissement
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Kurtosis.html
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
En théorie des probabilités et en statistique, le kurtosis (du grec κύρτωσις, « courbure », dérivé de κυρτός, « courbe, arrondi, bossu »), plus souvent traduit par coefficient d’aplatissement ou coefficient d’aplatissement de Pearson, correspond à une mesure de l’aplatissement, ou a contrario de la pointicité, de la distribution d’u

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
ANCOVA or analysis of covariance is a data transformation which evaluates if population means of a dependent variable are equal across levels of a categorical independent variables while controlling for the effects of other continuous variable s, known as covariates. Therefore, when performing ANCOVA, we are adjusting the dependent variable means to what they would be if all group

Orlaith Burke
L&apos;analyse de la covariance (ANCOVA) est une méthode statistique visant à tester, par un modèle linéaire général, l&apos;effet sur une variable dépendante continue d&apos;une ou plusieurs variables indépendantes catégorielles, indépendamment de l&apos;effet d&apos;autres facteurs quantitatif continus, dits covariables. En d&apos;autres termes, l&apos;ANCOVA est une combinaison entre une ANOVA et une régression de telle sorte que l&apos;ANCOVA permet de tester si certains facteurs ont un effet sur la variable résultat après avoir enlevé la variance due aux covariables. L&apos;inclusion de covariables peut accroître la puissance statistique parce qu&apos;elles sont la cause d&apos;une certaine variabilité.
adapted from wikipedia
Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Analyse_de_covariance
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://campus.cerimes.fr/genetique-medicale/enseignement/genetique_2/site/html/1.html
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium test is a statistical test which aims to evaluate if a population&apos;s proportion of allele is stable or not. It is used as means of quality control to evaluate possibility of genotyping error or population structure.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Proposée en 1908 indépendamment par le mathématicien anglais Hardy et le médecin allemand Weinberg, la loi de Hardy-W

Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO: adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardy–Weinberg_principle)
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odds_ratio
Orlaith Burke
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/art

Odds ratio is a ratio that measures effect size, that is the strength of association between 2 dichotomous variables, one describing an exposure and one descr

Jean-marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
L’odds ratio (OR), également appelé rapport des chances, rapport des cotes1 ou risque relatif rapproché2, est une mesure statistique, souvent utilisée en épidémiologie, exprimant le degré de dépendance entre des variables aléatoires qualitatives. Il est utilisé en inférence bayésienne et en régression logistique, et permet de mesurer 

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
sphericity testing objective is a statistical objective of a data transformation which aims to test a null hypothesis of sphericity holds.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
L&apos;objectif de test de sphéricité est un objectif statistique de transformation de données qui vise à tester une hypothèse nulle de sphéricité.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://www.tc3.edu/instruct/sbrown/stat/anova1.htm#ANOVAprereq
Tukey Honestly Significant Difference (HSD) test is a statistical test used following an ANOVA test yielding a statistically significant p-value in order to determine which means are different, to a given level of significance. The Tukey HSD tes

Test de la différence franchement significative
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
IMPORTANT: Do Not to confuse the Tukey HSD test with Tukey Mean Difference Test (Bland-Altman test)
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Le test Tukey de la différence franchement significative (HSD) est un test statistique utilisé à la suite d&apos;un test ANOVA donnant une valeur P statistiquement significative afin de déterminer quels moyenness sont différentss, à un niveau de signification donné. Le test HSD de Tuk

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
STATO
is a population whose individual members realize (may be expressed as) a combination ofinclusion rule values specifications or resulting from a sampling process (e.g. recruitment followed by randomization to group) on which a number of measurements will be carried out, which may be used as input to statistical tests and statistical inference.
En statistique, un échantillon est un ensemble d&apos;individus représentatifs d&apos;une population. L&apos;échantillonnage vise à obtenir une meilleure connaissance d&apos;une ou plusieurs population(s) ou sous-populations(s) par l&apos;étude d&apos;un nombre d&apos;échantillons jugé statistiquement représentatif. Le recours à un plan d&apos;échantillonnage répond en général à une contrainte pratique (manque de temps, de place, évaluation destructive d&apos;une production, coût financier…) interdisant l&apos;étude exhaustive de la population.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89chantillon_(statistiques)
Jean-Marc Meunier
A non-negative integer defining how many combination of factor levels (or treatments in the statistical sense) are to be used in a study.
C&apos;est un entier nul ou positif définissant combien de combinaison de niveaux de facteur (outraitement au sens statistique) qui peuvent être utilisées dans une étude.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/ConfidenceInterval.html
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2689604/
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intervalle_de_confiance
Orlaith Burke
A confidence interval is a data item which defines an range of values in which a measurement or trial falls corresponding to a given probability.
Jean-Marc Meunier
En mathématiques, un intervalle de confiance permet de définir une marge d&apos;erreur entre les résultats d&apos;un sondage et un relevé exhaustif de la population totale. Plus généralement, l&apos;intervalle de confiance permet d&apos;évaluer la précision de l&apos;estimation d&apos;un paramètre statistique sur un échantillon.
Le test de sphéricité de Mauchly est un test statistique qui évalue si la variance des différences entre toutes les combinaisons des groupes est égale, une propriété connue sous le nom de «sphericity» dans le contexte de mesures répétées. Il est utilisé par exemple avant l&a

the Mauchly&apos;s test for sphericity is a statistical test which evaluates if the variance of the differences between all combinations of the groups are equal, a property known as &apos;sphericity&apos; in the context of repeated measures. It is used for instance p

Test de sphéricité
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
AGB-PRS, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_power), polled June 10th, 2013
Philippe Rocca-Serra
the statistical test power is data item which is about a statistical test and is obtained by subtracting the false negative 

https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puissance_statistique
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
En statistique, la puissance d&apos;un test est la probabilité de rejeter l&apos;hypothèse nulle (par exemple l&apos;hypothèse selon laquelle les groupes sont identiques au regard d&apos;une variable) sachant que l&apos;hypothèse nulle est incorrecte (en réalité les groupes sont différents). On peut l&apos;exprimer sous la forme 1-β où β est le risque de 2e espèce c&apos;est-à-dire le risque de ne pas démontrer que deux groupes sont différents alors qu&apos;ils le sont dans la réalité
Spearman&apos;s rank correlation coefficient is a correlation coefficient which is a nonparametric measure of statistical dependence between two ranked variables. It assesses how well the relationship between two variables can be described using a monotonic function. If there are no repeated data values, a perfect Spearman correlation of +1 or −1 occurs when each of the variables is a perfect 

Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spearman%27s_rank_correlation_coefficient
Coefficient de corrélation calculé sur les numéros d&apos;ordre des valeur

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Rho de Spearman
http://www.modalisa.com/support/lexique/correlation-rangs-spearman.php
Spearman&apos;s rho
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/F-Distribution.html
the F-distribution is a continuous probability distribution which arises in the testing of whether two observed samples have the same variance.
En théorie des probabilités et en statistiques, la loi de Fisher ou encore loi de Fisher-Snedecor ou encore loi F de Snedecor est une loi de probabilité continue. Elle tire son nom des statisticiens Ronald Aylmer Fisher et George Snedecor. La loi de Fisher survient très fréquemment en tant que distribution de l&apos;hypothèse nulle dans des tests statistiques, comme les tests du ratio de vraisemblance, dans les test de Chow utilisés en économétrie, ou encore dans l&apos;analyse de la variance (ANOVA) via le test de Fisher.
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loi_de_Fisher
Snedecor Fisher distribution
Orlaith Burke
Fisher distribution
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
STATO
a planned process which etablishes and states the differenthypothesis to be evaluated during a null hypothesis statistical test
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Une hypothèse alternative estune hypothèse opposée à l&apos;hypothèse nulle
An alternative hypothesis is an hypothesis defined in a statistical test that is the opposite of the null hypothesis.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
is a data item formed by dividing the fluorescence intensity obtained in one channel to that obtained in the other channel, typically the case when considering 2-color microarray data when imaging is done for Cy3 and Cy5 dyes.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
discretization as a processing converting a continuous variable into a polychotomous variable by concretizing a set of discretization rules
La discrétisation est une transformation d&apos;une variable continue en une variable polychotomique en appliquant un ensemble

AGB,PRS adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discretization)
Orlaith Burke
Une population stratifiée est une population résultant d&apos;une stratification de lapopulation avant le processus d&apos;échantillonnage etqui vise à produire des sous-populations homogènes d&apos;une population hétérogène en appliquant un ou plusieurs critères de stratification
Orlaith Burke
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a stratum population is a population resulting from a population stratification prior to sampling process which aims to produce homogenous subpopulations from an heterogeneous population by applying one or more stratification criteria

a null hypothesis which states that a given matrix is proportional to a Wishart-distributed covariance matrix
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
C&apos;est une hypothèse nulle qui postule qu&apos;une matrice donnée est proportionnelle à une matrice de covariance basé sur une distribution de Wishart.
STATO
L&apos;ajustement du modèle est un processus de transformation de données qui évalue si un modèle représente de manière appropriée un ensemble de données. Un processus d&apos;ajustement demodèle teste la qualité de l&apos;ajustement du modèle aux données.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Model fitting is a data transformation process which evaluates if a model appropriately represents a dataset. A model fitting process tests the goodness of fit of the model to the data
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran

Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Erreur de type 2
Le taux de faux négatif est une donnée qui indique la proportion de détection manquée des éléments connus répondant aux critères de détection
Philippe Rocca-Serra
the false negative rate is a data item which denotes the proportion of missed detection of elements known to be meeting the detection criteria
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO, adapted from
Jean-Marc Meunier
aleatory variable
stochastic variable
Orlaith Burke



Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variable_al%C3%A9atoire
a random variable (or aleatory variable or stochastic variable) in probability and statistics,is a variable whose value is subject to variations due to chance (i.e. randomness, in a mathematical sense)
En théorie des probabilités, une variable aléatoire est une application définie sur l&apos;ensemble des éventualités, c&apos;est-à-dire l&apos;ensemble des résultats possibles d&apos;une expérience aléatoire. Ce furent les jeux de hasard qui amenèrent à concevoir les variables aléatoires, en associant à une éventualité (résultat du lancer d&apos;un dé, d&apos;un tirage à pile ou face, d&apos;une roulette, ...) un gain. Cette association éventualité-gain a donné lieu par la suite à la conception d&apos;une fonction de portée plus générale. Le développement des variables aléatoires est associé à la théorie de la mesure.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
group assignment based on blocking variable specification is a kind of group assignment process which takes into account the levels assumed by a blocking variable to allocate subjects or experimental units to a treatment group
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
L&apos;affectation de groupe basée sur la spécification de la variable de blocage est un type de processus d&apos;affectation de groupe qui prend en compte les niveaux d&apos;une variable de bloc pour allouer des sujets ou des unités expérimentales à un groupe de traitement.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Traduction à vérifier
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
A testing objective to ensure that the sample used in a statistical test actually follows a normal distribution.
Un objectif de test pour s&apos;assurer que l&apos;échantillon utilisé dans un test statistique suit en fait une distribution normale.
Une distribution de probabilité est une entité de support d&apos;information qui spécifie la probabilité de la valeur d&apos;une variable aléatoire.Pour une variable aléatoire discrète, une formule mathématique donne la probabilité de chaque valeur de la variable.Pour une variable aléatoire continue, une courbe décrite par une formule mathématique spécifie, au moyen d&apos;intervalle dans la courbe, la probabilité que la variable tombe dans un intervalle particulier.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
A probability distribution is a information content entity that specifies the probability of 

Loi de probabilité
Philippe Rocca-Serra
C&apos;est un objectif de test pour s&apos;assurer que les variances des différents groupes utilisés dans un test statistique sont similaires (c&apos;est-à-dire pas trop différentes).
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
homoschedacity testing objective
STATO
It is a testing objective to ensure the variances of the different groups used in a statistical test are similar (i.e. not too different). 
Orlaith Burke
Objectif de test de l&apos;homoscédasticité
Jean-Marc Meunier
Gaussian distribution
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loi_normale
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/NormalDistribution.html
a normal distribution is a continuous probability distribution described by a probability distri

En théorie des probabilités et en statistique, la loi normale est l&apos;une des lois de probabilité les plus adaptées pour modéliser des phénomènes naturels issus de plusieurs événements aléatoires. Elle est en lien avec de nombreux objets mathématiques dont le mouvement brownien, le bruit blanc gaussien ou d&apos;autres lois de probabilité. Elle est également appelée loi gaussienne, loi de Gauss ou loi de Laplace-Gauss des noms de Laplace (1749-1827) et Gauss (1777-1855), deux mathématiciens, astronomes et physi

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statvartypes.html
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
ordinal variable is a categorical variable wherethe discrete possible values are ordered orcorrespond to an implicit ranking
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltan
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
ranked variable
Orlaith Burke
La variable ordinal est une variable catégorielle où les valeurs discrètes possibles sont ordonnées ou correspondent à un classement implicite.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Chi-square probability distribution with k degrees of freedom is a theoretical probability distribution whichcorresponds to the distribution of a sum of the squares of k independent standard normal random variables.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
La distribution de probabilité de Chi-carré avec k degrés de liberté est une distribution de probabilité théorique qui correspond à la répartition d&apos;une somme des carrés de k variables indépendantes standard normalisées.
Espérance mathématique
μ
first moment
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
La valeur attendue (ou l&apos;attente, l&apos;espérance mathématique, EV, moyenne ou premier moment) d&apos;une variable aléatoire est un élément de données qui correspond à la moyenne pondérée de toutes les valeurs possibles que cette variable aléatoire peut prendre. Les poids utilisés pour calculer cette moyenne correspondent aux probabilités dans le cas d&apos;une variable aléatoire discrète, ou des densités dans le cas d&apos;une variable aléatoire continue. D&apos;un point de vue théorique rigoureux, la valeur attendue est l&apos;intégrale de la variable aléatoire par rapport à sa mesure de probabilité.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
mean
the expected value (or expectation, mathematical expectation, EV, mean, or the first moment) of a random variable is a data item which corresponds to the weighted average of all possible values that this random variable can take on. The weights used in computing this average correspond to the probabilities in case of a discrete random variable, or densities in case of a continuous random variable. From a rigorous theoretical standpoint, the expected value is the integral of the random variable with respect to its probability measure.
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expected_value
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Sensibilité
La sensibilité, ou la probabilité que le test soit positif si la maladie est présente, se mesure chez les malades seulement. Elle est donnée par la rapport VP/(VP+FN) où VP représente le nombre de vrais positifs et FN le nombre de vrais négatifs
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
sensitivity
recall
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sensibilit%C3%A9_et_sp%C3%A9cificit%C3%A9
Orlaith Burke


Jean-Marc Meunier
IL y a une divergence dans la formule. A revoir.
sensitivity is a measurement datum qualifying a binary classification test and is computed by substracting the false negative rate to the integral numeral 1
a residual is a data item which is the output of an error estimate or model fitting process and which is an observable estimate of the unobservable error
Orlaith Burke
Un résidu est une données issue d&apos;une estimation d&apos;erreur ou d&apos;un processus d&apos;ajustement d&apos;un modèle et qui est une estimation observable de l&apos;erreur non observable.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
The standard deviation of a random variable, statistical population, data set, or probability distribution is a measure of variation which correspond to the average distance from the mean of the data set to any given point of that dataset. It also corresponds to the square root of its variance. 
Philippe Rocca-Serra
σ
L&apos;écart type (standard deviation en anglais), aussi orthographié écart-type, est une notion mathématique définie en probabilités et appliquée à la statistique. En probabilité, l&apos;écart type est une mesure de la dispersion d&apos;une variable aléatoire ; en statistique, il est une mesure de dispersion de données. Il est défini comme la racine carrée de la variance ou, de manière équivalente, comme la moyenne quadratique des écarts par rapport à la moyenne. Il a la même dimension que la variable aléatoire ou la variable statistique en question.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_deviation
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran


high content screening is a kind of investigation which uses a standardized cellular assays to test the effect of substances (RNAi or small molecules) held in libraries on a cellular phenotype. it relies on microscopy imaging and or flow-cytometry, robotic handling to ensure fast and high-throughput.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
high throughput screening
Orlaith Burke
Kendall rank correlation coefficient
STATO, adapted from wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kendall_tau_rank_correlation_c

Kendall&apos;s tau (τ) coefficient
Le t

http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/t/tau.html
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Kendall&apos;s correlation coefficient is a correlation coefficient between 2 ordinal variables (natively or following a ranking procedure) and may be used when the conditions for computing Pearson&apos;s correlation are not met (e.g linearity, normality of the 2 continuous variables)
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erreur_statistique


Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
L&apos;erreur statistique est une donnée indiquant la quantité par laquelle une observation diffère de la valeur attendue, en fonction de l&apos;ensemble de la population statistique dans laquelle l&apos;unité statistique a été aléatoirement.
statistical error is an data item denoting the amount by which an observation differs from the expected value, being based on the whole statistical population from which the statistical unit was chosen randomly
Dans les représentations graphiques de données statistiques, la boîte à moustaches1 (aussi appelée diagramme en boîte, boîte de Tukey 2ou box plot en anglais) est un moyen rapide de figurer le profil essentiel d&apos;une série statistique quantitative. Elle a été inventée en 1977 par John Tukey, mais peut faire l&apos;objet de certains aménagements selon les utilisateurs. Son nom est la traduction de Box and Whiskers Plot.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bo%C3%AEte_%C3%A0_moustaches
Tukey, J. W. &quot;Box-and-Whisker Plots.&quot; §2C in Exploratory Data Analysis. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, pp. 39-43, 1977.
A box and whisker plot is appropriate to represent the characteristics oc a distribution.
box plot
a box plot is a graph which plots datasets relying on their quartiles and the interquartile range to create the box and the whiskers 
Jean-Marc Meunier
Boite de Tukey
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Tukey box and whisker plot
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Relative risk is a measurement datum which denotes the risk of an &apos;event&apos; relative to an &apos;exposure&apos;. Relative risk is calculated by forming the ratio of the probability of the event occurring in the exposed group versus the probability of this event occurring in the non-exposed group.
risk ratio
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Risque_relatif
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Le risque relatif (RR) est une mesure statistique souvent utilisée en épidémiologie, mesurant le risque de survenue d&apos;un événement dans un g

Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Woolf&apos;s test is a statistical test which evaluates the null hypothesis that odds ratio are the same accross all strata of population under investigation
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://people.umass.edu/biep640w/pdf/4.%20%20Categorical%20Data%20Analysis%202012.pdf
Le test de Woolf est un test statistique qui évalue l&apos;hypothèse nulle selon laquelle l&apos;oods ratio est le même dans toutes les couches de la population étudiée.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
nuisance variable
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a blocking variable is a independent variable which is used in a blocking process part of an experiment with the purpose of maximizing the signal coming from the main variable.
Une variable de bloc est une variable indépendante qui est utilisée dans un plan en blocs pour une expérience dans le but de maximiser le signal provenant de la variable principale.
Traduction sans doute à revoir
https://onlinecourses.science.psu.ed

Variable parasite
Orlaith Burke
https://onlinecourses.science.psu.edu/stat503/node/18
A continuous variable is one for which, within the limits the variable ranges, any value is possible.
http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statvartypes.html
http://davidmlane.com/hyperstat/A97418.html
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
&quot;Time to solve an anagram problem&quot; is continuous since it could take 2 minutes, 2.13 minutes etc. to finish a problem
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Une variable continue est une variable qui, dans les limites de son intervalle de variation, peut prendre une infinité de valeurs.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://udel.edu/~mcdonald/statvartypes.html
a categorical variableis a variablewhich that can only assume a finite numberof value and cast observation in a small number of categories
discrete variable
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une variable nominale décrit un nom ou une catégorie. Contrairement à une variable ordinale, les noms ou les catégories possibles ne suivent pas un ordre naturel. Le sexe et le genre de logement en sont des exemples. Dans le tableau 1, la variable « Mode de transport pour se rendre au travail » est une variable nominale, parce qu&apos;elle décrit une catégorie de mode de transport.
Orlaith Burke
http://www.statcan.gc.ca/edu/power-pouvoir/ch8/5214817-fra.htm
nominal variable
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Variable nominale
qualitative factor

the objective of a data transformation to test a null hypothesis of absence of difference within subject holds.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
C&apos;est un objectif d&apos;une transformation de données pour tester une hypothèse nulle d&apos;absence de différence au sein du sujet.
STATO
The allele frequency is a data item which denotes the incidence of a gene variant in a population. It is calculated as a ratio, by dividing the number of copies of a particular allele by the number of copies of all alleles at the genetic place (locus) in a population.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://www.nature.com/scitable/definition/allele-frequency-298
Philippe Rocca-Serra
C&apos;est un objectif de transformation de données pour tester une hypothèse nulle d&apos;absence de différence entre des groupes d&apos;individus.
the objective of a data transformation to test a null hypothesis of absence of difference withing subject holds.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
STATO
L&apos;objectif de transformation de donnée pour tester une hypothèse nulle d&apos;absence de différence entre les sujets de différents groupes.
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhattan_plot
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
a manhattan plot for gwas is a kind of scatter plot used to facilitate presentation of genome-wide association study (GWAS) data. Genomic coordinates are displayed along the X-axis, with the negative logarithm of the association P-value for each single nucleotide polymorphism displayed on the Y-axis.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Un diagramme de Manhattan est une sorte de diagramme de dispersion utilisé pour faciliter la présentation des données d&apos;étude d&apos;association à l&apos;échelle du génome (GWAS). Les coordonnées génomiques sont affichées le long de l&apos;axe X, avec le logarithme négatif de la valeur P de l&apos;association pour chaque polymorphisme nucléotidique unique affiché sur l&apos;axe des Y.
Un ou un plusieursde groupes domestiques liées par des des relation de descendance d&apos;un ancètre commun, le mariage ou l&apos;adoption.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
import from Pop

Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/PCO_0000020
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
A domestic group, or a number of domestic groups linked through descent (demonstrated or stipulated) from a common ancestor, marriage, or adoption.
http://www.ats.ucla.edu/stat/sas/library/repeated_ut.htm
L&apos;ANOVA à mesures répétées est une sorte d&apos;ANOVA développée spécifiquement pour des observations non indépendantes, telles qu&apos;elles sont trouvées lors de mesures répétées sur l&apos;unité expérimentale d&apos;échantillon. L&apos; ANOVA à mesures répétées est plus sensible à la condition de la normalité (évaluation à l&apos;aide du test de Bartlett), dans le cas de groupes non-équilibrés (c&apos;est-à-dire différentes tailles de populations d&apos;échantillons)
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Thomas Nichols
Analyse de variance sur des mesures répétées
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
adapted from wikipedia and https://statistics.laerd.com/statistical-guides/repeated-measures-anova-statistical-guide-3.php
discussion in https://github.com/ISA-tools/stato/issues/28
repeated measure ANOVA is a kind of ANOVA specifically developed for non-independent observations as found when repeated measurements on

ANOVA for correlated samples
Jean-Marc Meunier
The Newman–Keuls or Student–Newman–Keuls (SNK) method is a stepwise multiple comparisons procedure used to identify sample means that are significantly different from each other. It was named after Student (1927), D. Newman, and M. Keuls. This procedure is often used as a post-hoc test whenever a significant difference between three or more sample means has been revealed by an analysis of variance (ANOVA). The Newman–Keuls method is similar to Tukey&apos;s range test as both procedures use Studentized range statistics.Compared to Tukey&apos;s range test, the Newman–Keuls method is more powerful but less conservative.
Le test de Newman-Keuls ou Student-Newman-Keuls (SNK) est une procédure de comparaison multiple par étapes utilisée pour identifier des moyennes d&apos;échantillonnage significativement différentes les unes des autres. Il a été nommé d&apos;après Student (1927), D. Newman et M. Keuls. Cette procédure est souvent utilisée comme test post-hoc chaque fois qu&apos;une différence significative entre trois ou plusieurs moyennes d&apos;échantillonnage ont été révélées par une analyse de variance (ANOVA).
Orlaith Burke


Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Une combinaison de facteur-facteur est l&apos;un des ensembles possibles de niveaux de facteurs résultant du produit cartésien d&apos;ensembles de facteurs et de leurs niveaux tels que définis dans un modèle factoriel.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
treatment combination
STATO
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://isogenic.info/html/9__treatments.html#factorial
a factor level combination is one a possible sets of factor levels resulting from the cartesian product of sets of factor and their levels as defined in a factorial design
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Le facteur de Bayes est un rapport entre 2 probabilités d&apos;observation de données selon 2 modèles distincts. Il est utilisé dans la sélection du modèle de Bayes pour évaluer quel modèle explique le mieux les données. Si K &lt;0, le modèle utilisé dans le terme dénominateur est pris en charge, si K&gt; 1, le modèle utilisé dans le terme de 



Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Bayes factor is a ratio between 2 probabilities of observing data according 2 distinct models. It is used in Bayes model selection to evaluate which model best explains the data. if K&lt;0, the model used in the denominator term is supported, if K&gt;1, the model used in t

Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courbe_ROC
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Courbe ROC
La fonction d’efficacité du récepteur, plus fréquemment désignée sous le terme « courbe ROC1 » (de l’anglais receiver operating characteristic, pour « caractéristique de fonctionnement du récepteur ») dite aussi caractéristique de performance (d&apos;un test) ou courbe sensibilité/spécificité, est une mesure de la performance d&apos;un classificateur binaire, c&apos;est-à-dire d&apos;un système qui a pour objectif de catégoriser des éléments en deux groupes distincts sur la base d&apos;une ou plusieurs des caractéristiques de chacun de ces éléments. Graphiquement, on représente souvent la mesure ROC sous la forme d&apos;une courbe qui donne le taux de vrais positifs (fraction des positifs qui sont effectivement détectés) en fonction du taux de faux positifs (fraction des négatifs qui sont détectés (incorrectement)).
receiver operational characteristics curve is a graphical plot which illustrates the performance of a binary classifier system as its discrimination threshold (aka cut-off point) is varied by plottingsensitivity vs (1 − specificity)
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Receiver_operating_characteristic
Courbe de sensibilité/spécificité
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le test de déséquilibre de transmission est un test statistique pour la liaison génétique entre le marqueur génétique et un trait dans les familles. Le test est robuste à la structure de la population.
TDT
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
TODO: need to modify restrictions to include family and trio
STATO , adapted wikipedia (from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transmission_disequilibrium_test), polled on June,2013
The transmission disequilibrium test is a statistical test for genetic linkage between genetic marker and a trait in families. The test is robust to population structure.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_distribution
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
En théorie des probabilités et en statistique, la loi binomiale modélise le nombre de succès obtenus lors de la répétition indépendante de plusieurs expériences aléatoires identiques. Une manière visuelle de représenter cette suite d&apos;expériences est d&apos;utiliser un arbre de probabilité : à chaque génération de l&apos;arbre, deux branches partent de chaque nœud, une pour le suc

The binomial distribution is a discrete probability distribution which describes the probability of k successes in n draws with replacement from

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loi_binomiale




Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
AGB, PRS
hit selection is a planned process which in screening processes such as high-throughput screening, lead to the identification of perturbing agent which cause the typical signal generated by a standardized assay to significantly differ from the negative control. The selection hitself results from meeting or exceeding selection threshold (for instance 6 sigma from the mean or SSMD value beyond 5 when compared to positive controls or below -5 when compared to negative controls
Philippe Rocca-Serra
pairing rule is a rule which is specifies the criteria for deciding on how to associated any 2 entities.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Une règle d&apos;appariement est une règle qui spécifie le critère pour décider de la façon d&apos;associer deux entités.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
STATO
TODO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
between group comparison statistical test is a statistical test which aims to detect differencebetween the means computing for each of the study group populations
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Un test statistique de comparaison entre groupes est un test qui a pour objectif de détecter la différence entre les moyennes calculées pour chaque population étudiée.
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Pearson product-moment correlation coefficient
The Pearson&apos;s correlation coefficient is a correlation coefficient which evaluates two continuous variables for association strength in a data sample. It assumes that both variables are normally dis

http://www.modalisa.com/support/lexique/coefficient-r-bravais-pearson.php
Coefficient de corrélation de Bravais-Pearson
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Indicateur permettant de juger la qualité de la liaison entre deux varia



Orlaith Burke
Pearson&apos;s r
r statistics
F statistic is a statistic computed from observations and used to produce a p-value in statistical test when compared to a F distribution. the F statistic is the ratio of two scaled sums of squares reflecting different sources of variability
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
La statistique F est une statistique calculée à partir des observations et utilisée pour produire une valeur p dans le test statistique par rapport à une distribution F. La statistique F est le rapport des deux sommes de carré reflétant les différentes sources de variabilité.
STATO
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Orlaith Burke
Breusch, T. S. and Pagan, A. R. (1979) A simple test for heteroscedasticity and random coefficient variatio

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Dans les statistiques, le test Breusch-Pagan, développé en 1979 par Trevor Breusch et Adrian Pagan [1], est utilisé pour tester l&apos;hétéroscédasticité dans un modèle de régression linéaire. Il teste si la variance des erreurs d&apos;une régression dépend des valeurs des variables indépendantes. Dans ce cas, l&apos;hétéroscériorité est vérifiée.
Adaptée de https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breusch%E2%80%93Pagan_test
Breusch-Pagan test is a statistical test which computes a score test of the hypothesis of constant error variance against the alternative that the error variance changes with the level of the response (fitted values), or with a li

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
http://www.ncbi.nl

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Added following a

hypergeometric test is a null hypothesis test which evaluates if a random variable follows a hypergeometric distribution. It is a test of goodness of fit to that distribution. The test is suited for situation aimed at assessing cases of sampling from a finite set without replacements. For instance, testing for enrichment or depletion of elements (e.g GO categories, genes)
Le test hypergéométrique est un test d&apos;hypothèse nulle qui évalue si une variable aléatoire suit une distribution hypergéométrique. C&apos;est un test de qualité de l&apos;ajustement à cette distribution. Le test est adapté à une situation visant à évaluer les cas d&apos;échantillonnage à partir d&apos;un ensemble fini sans remplacement. Par exemple, les tests d&apos;enrichissement ou d&apos;épuisement des éléments (par exemple, les catégories GO, les gènes).
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran

Un testunilatéralest un test statistique qui, en supposant une répartition de probabilité non baisée, cherche àévaluer une seule hypothèseorientée 

one sided test
Orlaith Burke
Added following a

Jean-Marc Meunier
a one-tailed test is a statistical test which, assuming an unskewed probability distribution, allocates all of the significance level to evaluate only one hypo



Philippe Rocca-Serra
two sided test
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Added following a

a two tailed test is a statistical test which assess the null hypothesis of absence of difference assuming a symmetric (not skewed) underlying probability distribution by allocating half of the significance level selected to each of the direction of change which could explain a difference (for example, a difference can be an excess or a loss).


Un test bilatéral est un test statistique qui évalue l&apos;hypothèse nulle d&apos;absence de différence en supposant une répartition de probabilité symétrique (non biaisée) en allouant la moitié du niveau de signification sélectionné à chacun sensqui pourrait expliquer une différence (par exemple , Une différence peut être un excès ou une perte).
Jean-Marc Meunier
For example, we may wish to compare the mean of a sample to a given value x using a t-test.Our null hypothesis is that the mean is equal to x. A two-tailed test will test both if the mean is significantly greater than x and if the mean significantly less than x. The mean is considered significantly different from x if the test statistic is in the top 2.5% or bottom 2.5% of its probability distribution, resulting in a p-value less than 0.05.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Devrait être une sous classe d&apos;hypothèse nulle
A null hypothesis which states that no difference exists between 2 or more groups being considered.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
model matrix
Une matrice d&apos;expérience est une entité support d&apos;information qui dénote une conception d&apos;étude. La matrice de d&apos;expérience est une matrice n par m où n, le nombre de lignes correspond au nombre d&apos;observations et où m, le nombre de colonnes correspond au nombre de variables indépendantes. Chaque élément de la matrice correspond à une valeur discrétisée représentant l&apos;un des niveaux de 

Added following a term request by Nolan Nichols: https://github.com/ISA-tools/stato/issues/9
a design matrix is an information content entity which denotes a study design. The design matrix is a n by m matrix where n the number of rows, corresponds to the number of observations (4 rows if quadruplicates) and where m, the number of columns corresponds to the number of independent variables. Each element in the matrix correspond to a discretized value representing one of the fa

Orlaith Burke
Plan d&apos;expérience
let&apos;s consider an experiment evaluating 2 compounds (aspirin &amp; ibuprofen)at 3 distinct dose levels (low, medium, high) and 4 time points post exposure (0h, 6h, 12h, 24h). Assuming the treatments are applied only once (no replication), the number of observation in a full factorial design is 2 x 3 x 4 = 24 so the design matrix would have 24 rows and 3 columns (1 per



Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
A contrast is the weighted sum of group means, the c_j coefficients represent the assigned weights of the means (these must sum to 0 for orthogonal contrasts)
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contrast_%28statistics%29
Camille Maumet
Term request by Nolan Nichols via https://github.com/ISA-tools/stato/issues/9
Un contraste est la somme pondérée des moyennes de groupe, les coefficients cj représentent les poids attribués aux moyennes (ceux-ci doivent être à 0 pour les contrastes orthogonaux).
Tom Nichols
Test binomial exact
Added following a

Philippe Rocca-Serra


Jean-Marc Meunier
Test binomial exact
scipy.stats.binom_test(x, 

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
La procédure de test binomial compare les fréquences observées des deux catégories d&apos;une variable dichotomique avec les fréquences que l&apos;on peut attendre d&apos;une distribution binomiale avec un paramètre de probabilité spécifié. Par défaut, le paramètre de probabilité pour les deux groupes est de 0,5. Pour modifier les probabilités, vous pouvez entrer un test de proportion pour le premier groupe. La probabilité pour le second groupe sera de 1 moins la probabilité spécifiée pour le premier groupe.
a binomial test is a statistical hypothesis test which evaluates if the observations made about a Bernoulli experiment , that is an experiment which tests the statistical significance of deviations from a theoretically expected distribution (the binomial distribution) of observations into 2 categories. It is a goodness of fit test.
Orlaith Burke
https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/fr/SSLVMB_22.0.0/com.ibm.spss.statistics.help/spss/base/idh_ntbi.htm
Evaluation of statistical inference o

L&apos;inférence statistique est un processus d&apos;élaboration des conclusions suite à l&apos;analyse des données en utilisant des méthodes statistiques (tests statistiques) et en évaluant s&apos;il faut rejeter ou accepter une hypothèse nulle
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
statistical inference is a process of drawing conclusions following data analysis using statistical methods (statistical tests) and evaluating whether to reject or accept null hypothesis
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Added following a

Covariance d&apos;une distribution à deux caractères, moyenne arithmétique des produits des écarts à la moyenne po

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra


Orlaith Burke
The covariance is a measurement data item about the strength of correlation between a set (

http://www.larousse.fr/dictionnaires/francais/covariance/20078
Jean-Marc Meunier
Letest det surest une sorte de test t de Student qui évalue si un échantillon donné peut être raisonnablement suppos

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
one sample t-test is a kind of Student&apos;s t-test which evaluates if a given sample can be reasonably assumed t

adapted f

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
two sample t-test
Letest t pour deux échantillons est un test statistique d&apos;hypothèse nulle qui est utilisé pour rejeter ou accepter l&apos;hypothèse d&apos;absence de différence entre les moyens sur 2 populatio

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran


Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
two sample t-test is a null hypothesis statistical test which is used to reject or accept the hypothesis of absence of difference between the means over 

Jean-Marc Meunier


En statistiques, le test t de Welch est une adaptation du test t de Student. Il peut être utilisé notamment pour tester statistiquement l’hypothèse d’égalité de deux moyennes avec deux échantillons de variances inégales
Welsh t-test
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_t_de_Welch
Welch, B. L. (1947). &quot;The generalization of &quot;Student&apos;s&quot; problem when several different population variances are involved&quot;. Biometrika 34 (1–2): 28–35. doi:10.1093/biomet/34.1-2.28
Welch t-test is a two sample t-test used when the variances of the 2 populations/samples are thought to be unequal (homoskedasticity hypothesis not verified). In this version of the two-sample t-test, the denominator used to form the t-statistics, does not rely on a &apos;pooled variance&apos; estimate.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Test t de Student avec deux échantillons de variances inégales
Jean-Marc Meunier


Jean-Marc Meunier
Chi2 test for goodness of fit
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Pearson&apos;s Chi-Squared test for goodnes of fit is a statistical null hypothesis test which is used to either evaluate goodness of fit of dataset to a Chi-Squared distribution
Le test Chi carré d&apos;ajustement est un test statistique d&apos;hypothèse nulle qui sert à évaluer la qualité de l&apos;ajustement de l&apos;ensemble de données à une distribution Chi carré.
Le test de Barnard est un test statistique exact utilisé pour déterminer s&apos;il existe des associations non aléatoires entre deux variables catégorielles. Il a été développé en 1949 par Barnard et est un test qui, la plupart du temps, est plus puissant que le test exact de Fisher.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
duplicate with OBI_0200176. so either MIREOT and add metadata and axioms or move from OBI
http://en.wikiped

Barnard&apos;s test is an exact statistical test used to determine if there are nonrandom associations between two categorical variables. It was developed in 1949 by Barnard and is a test which is, most times, more powerfull that the Fisher exact test
Orlaith Burke
L&apos;effet normalisé de la moyenne quadratique est un élément de données qui indique la taille de l&apos;effet dans le contexte de l&apos;analyse de variance et correspond à la racine carrée de la moyenne arithmétique des effets standard de p (effets normalisés pour être exprimés en u

Philippe Rocca-Serra
Ψ
Jean-Marc Meunier
http://www.statsoft.fr/concepts-statistiques/glossaire/e/effet-centre.html
root-mean-square standardized effect is a data item which denotes effect size in the context of analysis of variance and corresponds to the square root of the arithmetic average of pstandardized effects(effects normalized to be expressed in standard deviation units).
http://www.statpower.net/Steiger%20Biblio/Steiger04.pdf
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effect_size#Eta-squared.2C_.CE.B72
Eta-squared est un estimateur biaisé de la variance expliquée par le modèle dans la population (il estime seulement l&apos;effet de la taille dans l&apos;échantillon). Eta-carré décrit le rapport de la variance expliqué de la variable dépendante par un prédicteur tout en contrôlant d&apos;autres prédicteurs, ce qui le rend analogue au r2. Cette estimation partage la faiblesse avec r2 que chaque variable supplémentaire augmentera automatiquement la valeur de η2. En outre, elle mesure la variance expliquée de l&apos;échantillon, et non la population, ce qui signifie qu&apos;il surestimera toujours la taille de l&apos;effet, bien que le biais diminue lorsque l&apos;échantillon augmente.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Eta-squared is a biased estimator of the variance explained by the model in the population (it estimates only the effect size in the sample). Eta-squared describes the ratio of variance explained in the dependent variable by a predictor while controlling for other predictors, making it analogous to the r2. This estimate shares the weakness with r2 that each additional variable will automatically increase the value of η2. In addition, it measures the variance explained of the sample, not the population, meaning that it will always overestimate the effect size, although the bias grows smaller as the sample grows larger.
Orlaith Burke


Jean-Marc Meunier
L&apos;oméga-carré est une estimation de taille d&apos;un effet pour la variance expliquée qui est moins biaisée que le coefficient eta-carré.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
omega-squared is a effect size estimate for variance explained which is less biased than the eta-squared coefficient.
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
le g Hedges est un estimateur de la taille de l&apos;effetsimilaire à celui de Cohen et est une mesure basée sur une différence standardisée. Cependant, le dénominateur, correspondant à un écart type combiné, est calculé différemment du coefficient d Cohen, en appliquant un facteur de correction (qui implique une fonction Gamma).


Philippe Rocca-Serra
Hedges&apos;s g is an estimator of effect size, which is similar to Cohen&apos;s d and is a measure based on a standardized difference. However, the denominator, corresponding to a pooled standard deviation, is computed differently from Cohen&apos;s d coefficient, by applying a correction factor (which involves a Gamma function).
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Le delta du Glass est un estimateur de la taille de l&apos;effet similaire à celui de Cohenoù le dénominateur ne correspond qu&apos;à l&apos;écart type du groupe témoin (ou du second groupe). Il est considéré comme moins biaisé que le d de Cohen pour estimer les tailles de l&apos;effet en fonction des moyenness et des distances entre les moyennes.


Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Glass&apos;s delta is an estimator of effect size which is similar to Cohen&apos;s d but where the denominator corresponds only to the standard deviation of the control group (or second group). It is considered less biais than the Cohen&apos;s d for estimating effect sizes based on means and distances between means.
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Orlaith Burke
Thomas Nichols
a contrast weight is a coefficient which multiplies a group mean, part of a linear combinaison defining a constrast as a weighted sum of group means, giving a &apos;weight&apos; to a specific group mean hence the name. 
Un poids dans un constraste est un coefficient qui multiplie une moyenne de groupe et fait partie d&apos;une combinaison linéaire définissant un constraste en tant que somme pondérée de moyennes de groupes, donnant un «poids» à un groupe spécifique d&apos;où le nom.


http://artax.karlin.mff.cuni.cz/r-help/library/nparcomp/html/weight.matrix.html
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Camille Maumet
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une matrice de poids est une entité support d&apos;informations qui contient un ensemble de poids, coefficients utilisés dans une somme pondérée de moyennes définissant un contraste
a contrast weight matrix is a information content entity which holds a set of contrast weight, coefficient used in a weighting sum of means defining a contrast
[1,0,0]
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Camille Maumet
STATO
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Tom Nichols
L&apos;estimation de contraste de poids est une estimation du paramètre de modèle qui résulte d&apos;un calcul à partir des données et qui est utilisé comme entrée pour un processus d&apos;ajustement du modèle.
Camille Maumet
contrast weight estimate is a model parameter estimate which results from the computation from the data and that is used as input to a model fitting process
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
Orlaith Burke
Tom Nichols
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
The Akaike information criterion (AIC) is a measure of the relative quality of a statistical model for a given set of data. As such, AIC provides a means for mode

Le critère d&apos;information d&apos;Akaike, (en anglais Akaike information criterion ou AIC) est une mesure de la qualité d&apos;un modèle statistique propos

Orlaith Burke
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crit%C3%A8re_d%27information_d%27Akaike
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7791040
Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://en.wikipedia.org/wi

Jean-Marc Meunier
Bayesian information criterion or Schwartz&apos;s Bayesian information criterion is a criterion for model selection among a finite set of models. It is based, in part, on the likelihood function and it is closely related to the Akai

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayesian_information_criterion
Le critère d&apos;information bayésien ou le critère d&apos;information bayésienne de Schwartz est un critère pour la sélection du modèle parmi un ensemble fini de modèles. Il repose en partie sur la fonction de vraisemblance et est étroitement lié au critère d

Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7791040
Schwarz, Gideon E. (1978). &quot;Estimating the dimension of a model&quot;. Annals of Statistics 6 (2): 461–464. doi:10.1214/aos/1176344136.
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une sélection de modèle statistique est une transformation de données basée sur le calcul d&apos;une valeur de qualité relative afin d&apos;évaluer et de sélectionner quel modèle explique le mieux les données.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
STATO
a statistical model selection is a data transformation which is based on computing a relative quality value in order to evaluate and select which model best explains data.
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Camille Maumet
Une structure de covariance est un élément de données qui fait partie d&apos;un modèle de régression et qui indique un pattern dans la matrice de covariance. La nature de la structure de covariance est spécifiée avant que l&apos;analyse de régression et la structure de covariance ne soient testées et évaluées à l&apos;aide de critères d&apos;information pour aider à choisir le modèle le plus adaptable.
http://www3.nd.edu/~kyuan/courses/sem/readpapers/benter.pdf
a covariance structure is a data item which is part of a regression model and which indicates a pattern in the covariance matrix. The nature of covariance structure is specified before the regression analysis and various covariance structure may be tested and evaluated using information criteria to help choose the most suiteable model
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Tom Nichols
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Mallows&apos; Cp is a data item which compares the precision and bias of the full model to models with a subset of the predictors thus helping to choose between multiple r

Philippe Rocca-Serra
http://support.minitab.com/en-us/minitab/17/topic-library/modeling-statistics/regression-and-correlation/goodness-of-fit-statistics/what-is-mallows-cp/
Orlaith Burke
Le Cp de Mallows est un élément de données qui compareprécision et biais du modèle complet aux modèles avec un sous-ensemble des prédicteurs, ce qui permet de choisir entre des modèles de régression multiples.Le Cp de Mallows est une fonction du nombre de paramètres utilisés dans le modèle en s&apos;appuyant sur la somme résiduelle des carrés pour calculer un score.Plus le CP est petit est, meilleure est le modèle. &quot;
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Le glossaire de l&apos;ISI assimile écart-type et erreur quadratique moyenne, qui ont l&apos;air différentes. A tirer au clair.
En statistiques, l’erreur quadratique moyenne d’un estimateur thetad’un paramètre de dimension 1 est une mesure caractérisant la « précision » de cet estimateur. Elle est plus souvent appelée « erreur quadratique », « moyenne » étant sous-entendu) ; elle est parfois appelée aussi « risque quadratique » ou désigné par son acronyme anglais MSE.
https://github.com/ISA-tools/stato/issues/35
Thomas Nichols
Jean-Marc Meunier
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
used as an unbiased estimator of teh variance for a regression model
https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erreur_quadratique_moyenne
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mean_squared_error#Regression
Camille Maumet
a residual mean square is a data item which is obtained by dividing the sum of squared residuals (SSR) by the number of degrees of freedom
http://support.minitab.com/en-us/minitab/17/topic-library/modeling-statistics/anova/anova-statistics/understanding-mean-squares/
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z-test
Jean-Marc Meunier
Camille Maument
Thomas Nichols
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Z-statistic is a statistic computed from observations and used to produce a p-value when compared to a Standard Normal Distribution in a statistical test called the Z-test.
La statistique Z est une statistique calculée à partir des observations et utilisée pour produire une valeur p par rapport à une distribution normale standard dans un test statistique appelé test Z.
Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Philippe Rocca-Serra
https://fr.wiktionary.org/wiki/d%C3%A9viance
Deviance is an indicator of fit and can be estimated by computing-2 times the log-likelihood ratio of the fitted model compa

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Au sens strict, la déviance est définie à partir de la vraisemblance dans le cas d’un modèle paramétrique. Soit un ensemble de n observations et un modèle avec les paramètres β0, β1..βn ; alors L(β0) est la vraisemblance du modèle n’utilisant que le paramètre β0, tandis que L(βn) est la vraisemblance du modèle complètement paramétrisé (L(βn) = 1 parce que le modèle est parfaitement ajusté). La déviance pour k paramètres est D(βk) = –2[log L(βk) – log L(βn)] = log [L(βn)/ L(βk)]2 = –2 log L(βk).
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deviance

Le critère d&apos;information de déviation (DIC) est une généralisation de la modélisation hiérarchique de l&apos;AIC (critère d&apos;information Akaike) et du BIC (critère d&apos;information bayésien, également connu sous le nom de critère de Schwarz). Il est particulièrement utile dans les problèmes de sélection du modèle bayésien où les distributions postérieures des modèles ont été obtenues par la simulation de la chaîne de Markov Monte Carlo (MCMC). Comme l&apos;AIC et le BIC, il s&apos;agit d&apos;une approximation asymptotique à mesure que la taille de l&apos;échantillon devient importante. Ce n&apos;est valable que lorsque la distribution postérieure est approximativement à 

Jean-Marc Meunier
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deviance_information_criterion
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
The deviance information criterion (DIC) is a hierarchical modeling generalization of the AIC (Akaike information criterion) and BIC (Bayesian information criterion, also known as the Schwarz criterion). It is particularly useful in Bayesian model selection problems where the posterior distributions of the models have been obtained by Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulation. Like AIC and BIC it is an asymptotic approximation as the sample size becomes large. It is only valid when the posterior distribution is app

http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2682718/
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
 Journal of the American Statistical Association, volume 98, pp. 879–899. doi:10.1198/016214503000000819
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
The focused information criterion is a measurement data item which aims at facilitating model selection. It was published in 2003 by Claeskens, G. and Hjort, N.L. (2003). &quot;The focused information criterion&quot;. Journal of the American Statistical Association, volume 98, pp. 879–899. doi:10.1198/016214503000000819
Le critère d&apos;information ciblé est un élément de mesure qui vise à faciliter la sélection du modèle. Il a été publié en 2003 par Claeskens, G. et Hjort, N.L. (2003). \ &quot;Le critère d&apos;information ciblé \&quot;. Journal de l&apos;American Statistical Association, volume 98, pp. 879-899. Doi: 10.1198 / 016214503000000819
Philippe Rocca-Serra
Philippe Rocca-Serra
A scatterplot matrix contains all the pairwise scatter plots of a set of variables on a single page in a matrix format.
Adapted from http://itl.nist.gov/div898/handbook/eda/section3/eda33qb.htm
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Jean-Marc Meunier
Une matrice de diagramme de dispersion contient tous les diagrammes de dispersion par paire d&apos;un ensemble de variables sur une seule page au format matriciel.


the sample mean of sample of size n with n observations is an arithmetic mean computed over n number of observ

Jean-Marc Meunier
Orlaith Burke
Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran
Philippe Rocca-Serra
C&apos;est la moyenne arithmétique des observations sur un échantillon statistique.
Orlaith Burke
Jean-Marc Meunier
La moyenne de la population ou la moyenne de la distribution est un paramètre d&apos;une distribution de probabilité ou d&apos;une population indicative de la tendance centrale des données. Pour une répartition continue de la probabilité, la moyenne de la population est calculée en utilisant la fonction de densité de probabilités, pour des distributions de probabilité discrètes, une fonction de densité de m

Alejandra Gonzalez-Beltran


the population mean or distribution mean is a parameter of a probability distribution or population indicative of the data dispersion. For continous probabibility distribution, the population mean is computed using the probability density function, for discrete probability distributions, a mass den

Philippe Rocca-Serra
</text>
                          <sha1>753hugogitqwnlby9d3k5rdzsa58oj1</sha1>
                        </revision>
                      </page>
                    </mediawiki>